<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Diatribae, or, Discourses upon select texts wherein several weighty truths are handled and applyed against the papist and the Socinian / by Henry Bagshaw.</title>
            <author>Bagshaw, Henry, 1632-1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 104 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29252</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B429</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25261</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08833615</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08833615</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41913</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29252)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41913)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1274:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Diatribae, or, Discourses upon select texts wherein several weighty truths are handled and applyed against the papist and the Socinian / by Henry Bagshaw.</title>
                  <author>Bagshaw, Henry, 1632-1709.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 186 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.H. for Ric. Chiswell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41913:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41913:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>DIATRIBAE;</hi> OR Diſcourſes UPON SELECT TEXTS: Wherein Several weighty Truths are handled and applyed againſt the PAPIST AND THE SOCINIAN. By <hi>HENRY BAGSHAW,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. H.</hi> for <hi>Ric. Chiſwell</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Churchyard,</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:41913:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41913:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right Honourable and Reverend Father in God, Nathaniel, Lord Biſhop of <hi>Durham.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have been long doubtful in my thoughts what Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to handle under ſo great a variety of Chriſtian Truths; but I do not doubt in the leaſt where I ſhould fix my Dedication; ſince your Lordſhip may challenge
<pb facs="tcp:41913:3"/>all my endeavours, whether I be barely conſider'd as a <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> of your <hi>Dioceſs,</hi> or far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as <hi>planted</hi> by your ſelf under the noble <hi>Influence</hi> of your <hi>Favour.</hi> As a <hi>Member,</hi> there is due from me all the <hi>Reverence</hi> of an <hi>Eſteem:</hi> as one <hi>planted,</hi> there is requiſite the peculiar <hi>tribute</hi> of a <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful mind</hi> in a return of ſome <hi>Fruit</hi> to your hands.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> I here offer to your Lordſhips view, and from thence to the World (how <hi>weakly</hi> ſoever they are written) yet I am ſure they have <hi>weight</hi> of <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>worth</hi> of <hi>Patronage</hi> to defend
<pb facs="tcp:41913:3"/>them. I here open from <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> Firſt, that heynous ſin of <hi>Impriſoning Truth,</hi> and the juſtneſs of Gods vengeance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd: Next, the natural In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference from <hi>Divine Promiſes,</hi> which is the exerciſe of all <hi>Piety:</hi> Thirdly, the cogent reaſon of adhering to our Lord Chriſt, becauſe He has <hi>words of Eternal life</hi> for his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: Laſt of all, the proper Benefit of his <hi>Death</hi> in that work of <hi>Juſtifying</hi> us, and the Peculiar Advantages of his <hi>Riſing:</hi> In all which points I have ſtrictly confin'd my ſelf within my <hi>Circle;</hi> and (as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion led me) reflected upon
<pb facs="tcp:41913:4"/>Two great <hi>Enemies</hi> to <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,</hi> which are the <hi>Papiſt</hi> and the <hi>Socinian;</hi> the one cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his <hi>Diana</hi> (which is <hi>the Church</hi>) the other magnifying as <hi>falſe</hi> a <hi>Goddeſs</hi> (which is <hi>his own Reaſon</hi>) to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it.</p>
            <p>I need not here publiſh your Lordſhips <hi>Zeal</hi> for our <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church,</hi> which you have abundantly demonſtrated to your own <hi>Clergy,</hi> nor the <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> of your <hi>Government,</hi> which we all taſte of: but ſince I am made ſo ſingular an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of your <hi>kindneſs</hi> both as to preſent and future encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, I take leave to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:41913:4"/>it to the world, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to acquaint your Lordſhip, That the great <hi>Temptation</hi> I had to write was my <hi>Senſe</hi> of it; where I hoped I might e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect ſome <hi>laſting Memorial;</hi> or (if the poorneſs of what is written ſhould hinder <hi>life,</hi>) yet the <hi>Candid Reader</hi> might give it one by conſidering your Lordſhips <hi>Name,</hi> and the <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> of the <hi>Writer.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am, my Noble Lord, Your Lordſhips Moſt obliged and ever faithful Servant, Henry Bagshaw.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Houghton le ſpring,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sept. 30. 1679.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:41913:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41913:5"/>
            <head>The Firſt Diſcourſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 1.18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For the wrath of God is revealed from Heaven againſt all ungodlineſs and unrighteouſneſs of men, who hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe words have reference to the ſixteenth verſe of the Chapter, wherein the Apoſtle ſtoutly defends the Charge of his Miniſtry, becauſe the <hi>Goſpel</hi> he preached, though it might ſeem to have a weak Subject <hi>(a Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Saviour)</hi> and as weak a Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer of that Subject <hi>(a deſpiſed Meſſenger)</hi> yet was <hi>the Power of God to Salvation.</hi> How it prov'd ſuch an effectual Inſtrument in Gods
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41913:6"/>hands to convert the World, He farther illuſtrates by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and Rules of it, as being a <hi>full revelation</hi> of his Will, both to accept the imperfect righteouſneſs of men, and to puniſh their wilful diſobedience. In the one it ſutes it ſelf to our <hi>higheſt Hopes,</hi> by that <hi>bleſſed Life</hi> it propounds; in the other it is applied to our <hi>greateſt Fears,</hi> by that <hi>curſed Death</hi> it threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens: ſo that none can poſſibly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the force of Religion, except at the ſame time their own paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be deſtroyd.</p>
            <p>Now what is Gods rule of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving men by, he tells us in the Verſe foregoing my Text; and with what clearneſs of diſcovery the Goſpel lays open the <hi>Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> of a Sinner, and <hi>Faith</hi> the condition preſcribed: but leſt this Faith ſhould be miſtaken (as if Heaven were the reward of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41913:6"/>Belief, and a bare relyance on Chriſt might buy out his purchaſe) he checks our confidence by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Manifeſtation of Gods Juſtice againſt Sinners, As <hi>the Juſt ſhall live by Faith,</hi> (whereby He means Faith that is the Principle of a new life,) ſo the Wicked ſhall die for their Impenitence; and both theſe ſtates the Goſpel reveals; a <hi>Light</hi> ſent us from above to work <hi>doubly</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, in <hi>refreſhing</hi> the Saint, and <hi>conſuming</hi> the Malefactor. <hi>For the wrath of God, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether the ſcope of theſe words be directed againſt the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> who were ſuch Rebels to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or againſt a mungrel ſort of them (the <hi>Gnoſticks</hi>) who were ſuch corrupters of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> I ſhall not here examine, but conſider them barely in themſelves as they point out to us a General Truth, which is this,</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:41913:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That the wrath of God againſt all kind of ſin, but eſpecially the ſin of thoſe who hold the Truth in Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, is plainly diſcovered in the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the management of this Truth it will be neceſſary to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Into the Nature of Gods Wrath, what it implyes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Why the Revelation of his Wrath is more peculiarly aſcrib'd to the Goſpel?</p>
            <p n="3">3. How juſtly it is exerciſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe Sinners who hold the Truth in Unrighteouſneſs.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Into the Nature of Gods <hi>Wrath,</hi> what it implyes.</p>
            <p>The holy Pen-men of Scripture that borrowed our Paſſions to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the manner of Gods dealing with us, teach us withal to abſtract from the weakneſs of them. Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in us ſhew the imperfectneſs
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41913:7"/>of our beings, that we need ſuch <hi>Principles</hi> to act by; and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectneſs too of our State, in that Trouble follows their <hi>Motion:</hi> And particularly this paſſion of <hi>Wrath</hi> is attended with a double one; either if you regard the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance it raiſes in the Soul up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſenſe of an Injury, or the poor limiting of it to Time in its effects of puniſhing: in neither ſenſe can it belong to God; for could He be diſturbed when provok'd, He would loſe the <hi>Happineſs of his State;</hi> could He be limited in his Vengeance, He would loſe the <hi>Glory of his Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore his Wrath in this place can ſignifie nothing elſe but a ſettled decree, or fixt will of puniſhing ſin eternally. This is a revenge proper to God, and it is this alone makes the Tranſgreſſor fear: In this ſenſe it is taken by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41913:8"/>
               <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> when he warns his hearers to <hi>flee from the Wrath to come;</hi> and by St. <hi>Paul</hi> when he ſpeaks of <hi>the day of Wrath;</hi> ſtyl'd ſo with an Emphaſis, to diſtinguiſh it from Gods other days of Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this world.</p>
            <p>Here a Day of Juſtice may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be termed <hi>Night</hi> for its dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Providence it ſelf ſeems to be clouded even in thoſe <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolts</hi> that come down; but the Day wherein the ſinners eternal Portion will be aſſigned, is a clear one; for it derives its diſtinguiſhing light from the ſcorching <hi>Flame</hi> that <hi>preys</hi> on him. Did not God thus puniſh the Offender, all his other Judgments would not bridle us, nor could there be a ſufficient Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his wrath, did it only <hi>light</hi> on the party, but not <hi>ſtay nor abide</hi> on him: Then Juſtice ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be his, when it is not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41913:8"/>common with man's; but man can temporally puniſh and be mocked to by the Sufferer, ſince that Death he inflicts as his higheſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, is but an end and eſcape from it. Wee all fooliſhly burn in our wrath, and the fires we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for othes carry a vain heart in them; they <hi>ſcorch and heal together,</hi> they diſſolve the body to aſhes, and <hi>cool</hi> it by doing ſo; but when Eternal Wrath ſeizes on us, when Everlaſting Burnings break forth, this is to give the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of pain, and no <hi>ſhadows.</hi> In this way God rewards mens evil deads, and by the terror of it keeps his infinite mercy from being abuſed; which is an Attribute that wicked men naturally ſtick to, and as hardly quit their hold of it in purſuit of their wickedneſs, were they not ſhaken off by another notion of Infinite Juſtice.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:41913:9"/>
            <p>I proceed to my ſecond Query,</p>
            <p n="2">II. Why the Revelation of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wrath is peculiarly aſcribed to the Goſpel? This is intimated in my Text; <hi>For the wrath of God</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>is revealed ſrom Heaven,</hi> that is immediately by the God of it, who deſcended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth to teach the world, and in an heavenly manner confirmed what He taught, ſealing by his Works the Truths He delivered.</p>
            <p>In handling this point I ſhall premiſe two things, which are here neceſſarily imply'd.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the eternal puniſhment of evil doers was a Truth decreed by God, before it was <hi>revealed:</hi> for Revelation gives no <hi>Eſſence</hi> to things, but only an <hi>Appearance</hi> to us: it is not a creating but a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering work; not a ſaying, let it be, but let it be with full Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. He that opens the earth,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41913:9"/>and produces thoſe ſtores it ſhuts up, does not thereby cauſe them to <hi>exiſt,</hi> but to be <hi>known;</hi> ſo when Gods wrath is ſaid here to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, it imports this, That it was firſt prepared. His decree was paſt from all eternity againſt ſin; having determined with himſelf to create Man, and govern him by Law, determin'd likewiſe a Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment anſwerable to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of the Lawgiver; from whoſe infinity Mans guilt ſhould ſwell up, ſo as to deſerve infinite Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
            <p>The Wrath then of God was ſure before-hand; only the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit we have by his revealing it is the applying of that Truth to us, whereby we are warned to ſeek out and provide a remedy of the Judgment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing I ſhall premiſe is, That till the Goſpel
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41913:10"/>came, the nature of Gods Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Juſtice was much hid and concealed.</p>
            <p>It is true the Gentiles had a Light from Heaven (which was the <hi>Light of Nature, the Candle of the Lord</hi>) and the Jews a more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial one, which was the <hi>Light of the Law</hi> to direct them; yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them contained a like evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of this Truth which the Goſpel affords us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Light of Nature the Gentiles were led by;</p>
            <p>I confeſs they had unalterably this dictate from it, that <hi>Wrath</hi> was the due pay of Offenders; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe men liv'd not up to the Principles of their Creation, they were therefore juſtly lyable to the Curſe; but how far that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould certainly extend, herein the Light fail'd to guide them. Reaſon it ſelf taught them to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41913:10"/>conclude the Wicked deſerv'd pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; but the Reaſon did not ſuffice to confirm that puniſhment in another World; for how Man could eternally ſubſiſt in a courſe of miſery they underſtood not, nor what conſiſtency there was of an immortal being with perpetual Torments <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was the Speech of one of their chief Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers; as if to <hi>Suffer</hi> and to be <hi>Mortal</hi> were one and the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>I need not mention the groſneſs of their miſtakes about the Nature of him they worſhipped, which is palpable to all from that Idolatry they invented; but their Error al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is alike notorious as to thoſe Motives they fail'd in, for urging Religion upon men. For when they denied the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the Body as <hi>Impoſsible,</hi> they muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently deny an <hi>Eternal Reward</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:41913:11"/>that was built on it. What we read in the <hi>Acts</hi> to be the profeſt <hi>Mockery</hi> of the Epicureans and Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icks (when St. <hi>Paul</hi> preached to them upon this Theme) was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the <hi>ſport</hi> of all the reſt; who ſcoff'd at any thing above Nature, and minding only the conſtant courſe of its operations, made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly their Eſtimate of Gods Power. But perhaps they deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd ſomewhat concerning the Life of the <hi>Soul;</hi> but then they did it very uncertainly (as <hi>Socrates</hi> in his Apology for himſelf before his Judges ſufficiently witneſſes) and if any of them were ſo poſitive as to affirm it, yet they made that ſtate after death ſo Aery and ſo Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantick, that neither the Juſt man could be refreſh'd, nor the Wicked frighted with that opinion.</p>
            <p>Go to their Stories of the <hi>Dark Regions</hi> below, and the <hi>Fiery Lake</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:41913:11"/>the Bad ſhould be caſt into; <hi>the Stone, the Wheel and the Vulture</hi> that was appointed them; theſe were the reports of their <hi>Poets,</hi> fit <hi>Prieſts</hi> for ſuch Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. Little did they work upon mens Faiths to believe them, who with their fabulous mixtures cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting Truth, hindred thereby the conviction of their Hearers. Hence their great ones were not mov'd with what was related to them; and the Vulgar did but conſider them as <hi>Tragedies</hi> upon a <hi>Stage;</hi> where Fears perhaps were raiſ'd in them from the Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of an Evil, and again eaſily cur'd with the conceit of a Fiction. In a word whatever Religion they had concerning another life, it was made by Fancy a wild Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and had no check upon conſcience to bind practice; ſo that to them the Wrath of God
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41913:12"/>here in my Text prov'd ſtill a Doctrine unknown.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us examine the Doctrin of the Jews, and that Light of Special Revelation which they enjoyed.</p>
            <p>It muſt be granted by all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that the Jews had their Covenant eſtabliſhed upon promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and threatnings of an Eternal Condition. God who choſe them out of all Nations to be his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and govern'd their State pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly by his Laws, did by this too diſtinguiſh them from the reſt of the World, that they had their Religion advanced by thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets He ſent amongſt them: whence we find it vindicated by Chriſt in a <hi>Diſpute,</hi> by <hi>Paul</hi> in a <hi>Defence,</hi> by <hi>Abraham</hi> in a <hi>Parable.</hi> Chriſts proves from thence his Doctrine of the <hi>Reſurrection, Paul</hi> his <hi>hope of the Promiſe,</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:41913:12"/>the <hi>different ſtate both of good and bad;</hi> which one would think were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſtop the mouths of our <hi>Modern Saducees</hi> when the <hi>Old</hi> were put to <hi>ſilence.</hi> And indeed who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall aſſert that the Jews had no ſuch benefit of Revelation, he muſt at once charge their <hi>Lawgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> with <hi>weakneſs,</hi> and their own <hi>Faith</hi> with <hi>abſurdity</hi> in cleaving to him.</p>
            <p>Yet however, this Law of the Jews (if compared with the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in the manner of its evidence) came not up to the excellency of that diſcovery. For the whole <hi>Moſaïck</hi> Oeconomy was made up of <hi>Types and Figures,</hi> and a thick <hi>Night</hi> continually overſpread their <hi>Tabernacle:</hi> Their <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> literally concerned the things of this life, and it required a pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Faith <hi>ſpiritually</hi> to interpret them: a vulgar eye would ſurely
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:41913:13"/>ſtay upon the Surface; but for to be able to take in the depth, this muſt proceed from a ſtrong en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning, which we read only a few were bleſt with, that like <hi>Moſes</hi> were carried up to ſee the hidden things of the <hi>Mount,</hi> when the generality ſtood below and ſaw nothing but <hi>Clouds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was then great need of a Saviour to appear, whether we regard Jew or Gentile; and that not only for the work of <hi>ſaving Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,</hi> but <hi>for redeeming Truth,</hi> which was ſo obſcur'd by the one, and loſt by the other. Now Chriſt has diſcharg'd his Office in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; and for this <hi>Prophet</hi> alone was reſerv'd all the glory of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation, who being <hi>the expreſs Image of his Fathers Perſon,</hi> was the Signifier alſo of his <hi>Will</hi> in the brighteſt Character.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:41913:13"/>
            <p>We know in the Creation <hi>Light</hi> was Gods <hi>firſt work,</hi> but in reſtoring of Religion his <hi>laſt</hi> He judg'd it not fit to bring bright day on his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at firſt, but by degrees to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare their weak ſight that it might be the better confirm'd; and when the full time came, the Goſpel was publiſhed, which put an end to farther diſcoveries and ſeal'd up the Viſion.</p>
            <p>This being premiſ'd, it remains I ſhould ſpeak one word to ſhew how <hi>Gods wrath</hi> by way of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency is revealed in the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> which will appear by conſidering,
<list>
                  <item>1. The Cleerneſs of it in the Letter.</item>
                  <item>2. The Publick Promulgation of it to the World.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Clearneſs of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; nothing can be more lively ſhown than the Sinners Hell, whoſe <hi>Worm</hi> is ſaid <hi>not to dye;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41913:14"/>is his <hi>Fire quenched:</hi> Nor does the <hi>Second Death</hi> ceaſe from <hi>hurting</hi> him. Should we now conclude with the <hi>Socïnian,</hi> Eternal Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be nothing elſe but Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or a Negation of Exiſtence, we muſt flatly deny thoſe phraſes of Scripture before mentioned; for the <hi>Worm</hi> it ſelf dies if its <hi>prey</hi> does ſo; the <hi>Fire</hi> is put out if the <hi>matter</hi> it feeds upon be not laſting; and the <hi>Second Death</hi> is not in the leaſt hurtful; if it imply nothing of <hi>torment.</hi> But beſides (were this granted them) what's become of the fierceneſs of Gods wrath, when neither felt nor endured? Where is his Judgment and ſevere rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning with evil doers, if they partake with Brutes in their end? It is folly to fear where Juſtice is not known; and conſequently a wide gap is opened by ſuch men to all impiety, when they take off
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:41913:14"/>the Terrors of Death, leaving men as unconcern'd to be nothing an hundred years hence, as an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years paſt to be unborn. O the <hi>vanity</hi> of that <hi>Reaſon</hi> they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to, which breaks the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Gods Laws! O the <hi>cruelty</hi> of their <hi>Compaſsion</hi> to Mans nature, whereby Religion it ſelf is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd! But Chriſt has otherwiſe inſtructed the World, and knowing it needful that <hi>Everlaſting Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ſhould be equally ſet before us with <hi>Life Eternal;</hi> He has joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them both in the Sentence, that we might be every way convinc'd Eternity is our lot, and therefore a full motive to Duty.</p>
            <p>In the Old Teſtament <hi>Tophet</hi> or the Valley of the Children of <hi>Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom</hi> (where their Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were ſacrificed to <hi>Moloch</hi>) was uſed by the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> as his greateſt Type and Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41913:15"/>of Hell: But how ſhort it fell of a Goſpel-deſcription will be made evident, if we conſult the <hi>place,</hi> the <hi>number</hi> it was prepared for, and the <hi>time</hi> of its burning: the <hi>place</hi> though deep, yet had <hi>bottom:</hi> the <hi>number</hi> though great, yet was <hi>limited to one People;</hi> and the <hi>time</hi> of its burning though fierce, yet had <hi>end.</hi> On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary the Goſpel reveals a <hi>bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Gulf,</hi> a <hi>multitude of all Nations</hi> that enter, and a <hi>perpetual duration</hi> of their torments. So that here we have a clear light of the Letter, wherein the Jews were defective.</p>
            <p>Neither does the excellency of a Revelation ſtop here, but we may conſider in the ſecond place:</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Publick Promulgation of it to the World; and the <hi>Seal</hi> it carries of an <hi>Univerſal Publiſhing,</hi> anſwerable to the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of him that came to ſet up an <hi>Univerſall
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41913:15"/>Kingdom.</hi> Behold, the Sentence of Divine Wrath was before hid with the Jews; but now the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of it ſpreads into all parts, and ſo it proves a new Light in regard of its extent through all quarters. That <hi>Sun of righteouſneſs,</hi> that has riſen, ſhines round about, not only <hi>with healing under his wings to preſerve,</hi> but with <hi>Flames</hi> too of vengeance to <hi>conſume.</hi> And this He manifeſted here on Earth, when he proclaimed the Glad-ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Salvation, and pronounc'd many a Bleſſing upon his People; yet leſt they ſhould forget the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of a Saviour, <hi>Woes</hi> and <hi>Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings</hi> were uſhered in, to allay and temper all his Miniſtry. Therefore thoſe that heard him, had reaſon to fear, and not think themſelves freed from <hi>Legal terrors,</hi> ſince the <hi>Thunder</hi> of <hi>Sinai</hi> continued ſtill, though the <hi>Darkneſs</hi> of it was gone.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:41913:16"/>
            <p>And as He thus awed them with his own Teaching, ſo He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned his Servants to do like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, when He ſent them abroad to teach all Nations. Mercy alone was not their Theme, nor the riches of Divine Grace in mans Redemption (which is ſuch wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come news to the receiver) but the Curſe was alſo annext, and the Charge of future Judgment; that if the former did pleaſe, the latter might bind. Before this, <hi>Ignorance</hi> might be ſome way pleaded by the Gentiles, that they obeyed not Gods Law, when Life and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality were not known; but after theſe were cleared up in the Goſpel, then their Condemnation was perfected. For now they could be no longer termed unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py for ſitting in <hi>Darkneſs</hi> and in the <hi>Shadow of Death,</hi> which is a kind of Sanctuary to the Pleader,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41913:16"/>but Wicked for <hi>loving</hi> the Shadow which is the beginning of Hell. Upon this account He no more <hi>winks</hi> or ſpares, but <hi>judicially eying</hi> their ſteps, denounces againſt them his heavieſt Judgment.</p>
            <p>I know many refer the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods Wrath to the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of it in the world, and make his outward Judgments upon ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners as ſo many Witneſſes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it. But were no higher meant than thoſe Inſtances, we ſhould be ſtill in the dark; convinc'd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he was wroth, but not wroth to a diſtinction, wherein Juſtice is revealed. None can ſpell out <hi>Characters</hi> of Providence, nor read the ſpecial <hi>Hand-writing</hi> upon the <hi>Wall</hi> without the benefit of <hi>Viſion.</hi> What is all our ſight of a juſt God here but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in a Riddle, a Riddle that has buſied Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers to reſolve, and hardned their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:41913:17"/>doubts by the enquiry? If Wrath be manifeſted, let the bad feel its burden; but alas! Gods Tempeſts here ſeem onely to fall upon his own Choſen: They may call it <hi>Grace</hi> thus to ſuffer, but it is <hi>Grace</hi> not ſeen, nor acknowledged by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, all the <hi>face</hi> of it being ſpoil'd in the <hi>Storm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other ſide the calm and luſtre of outward good, this is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally the wicked mans ſhare; we may call it <hi>Puniſhment</hi> thus to flouriſh, but it is a <hi>Puniſhment de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.</hi> Now to break up the <hi>Pit</hi> and ſhew thoſe Treaſures of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance ſhut up there; to ſearch into a wicked mans Fate, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Miſeries that follow it; to repreſent him naked in his Grave, and awak'd afterwards in that nakedneſs for ſcourging, this is properly to reveal Wrath, and to the Goſpel we muſt owe ſuch a Diſcovery.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:41913:17"/>
            <p>Thus much for my Second Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. There remains the Third to diſcuſs, which is this.</p>
            <p n="3">III. How juſtly it is exerciſed upon thoſe who hold the Truth in Unrighteouſneſs?</p>
            <p>In diſcuſſing this Head I ſhall firſt open the <hi>Charge,</hi> and then it will be eaſie to prove the juſtneſs of the <hi>Sentence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Charge</hi> laid againſt the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is not <hi>error</hi> of mind, nor <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of paſſion, nor <hi>decay</hi> of nature (which are Guilt attended with an Apology) but the <hi>tyranny</hi> of a <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt heart;</hi> That hating the Empire of <hi>Truth,</hi> takes it <hi>priſoner</hi> to be freed from its Government: for ſo the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> properly ſignifies, namely forcibly to withhold or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Truth, that is, to obſtruct the power of Religion.</p>
            <p>What a high piece of injuſtice
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:41913:18"/>this is, will be evidenc'd if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard,
<list>
                  <item>1. The Act in it ſelf.</item>
                  <item>2. The Motives that lead men to it.</item>
                  <item>3. The Effects that flow from it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the Act; it is no leſs than the ſeizure of a <hi>Soveraign Prince;</hi> for ſuch <hi>Truth,</hi> is; and therefore juſtly demands to have Juriſdiction in the ſoul, and like Light to ſpread in its full liberty. What have Subjects to do with fettering Princes, whom they are bound to obey, or keeping them in the dark when they ought to be viſible in the Throne? Kings are only at <hi>Babylon</hi> led captive: There they have <hi>their eyes put out, and their feet bound,</hi> that they can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee nor walk abroad: So the <hi>Chriſtian Law</hi> (that ought to rule in the World) is at <hi>Rome</hi> barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41913:18"/>uſed; a place eminent for <hi>kindling</hi> of <hi>Lamps,</hi> and for <hi>ſmother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of <hi>Light;</hi> for <hi>adorning</hi> of <hi>Altars,</hi> and for <hi>corrupting</hi> the <hi>Sacrifice.</hi> What I beſeech you is all their Worſhip but <hi>blind and lame,</hi> Truth being ſo ill rack'd with their handling, that they can only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint us with the deformities of its body? The <hi>Priſon</hi> it ſuffers in is that of <hi>One Language,</hi> hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to the Prieſts themſelves; the <hi>Eyes</hi> it has are thoſe Figur'd ones of an <hi>Idoll,</hi> that need the gildings of Art to be own'd: the <hi>Feet</hi> are the ſupports of a <hi>Tradition</hi> which requires an <hi>Implicit Faith,</hi> that is, Faith of the ſame <hi>lameneſs.</hi> Who that ſees Truth in this ſhape will not ſay it is vilify'd by its profeſſors, when the bare with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding it from others is a high Act of Injuſtice? For that Act is a withholding of the Birth-right
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:41913:19"/>and Inheritance of Men, and a fruſtrating of Gods purpoſe in the gift of it; who as he has deſign'd the <hi>Elements of Nature</hi> to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly enjoyed for our <hi>Bodily</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation, ſo he has alſo deſign'd the <hi>Elements of Truth</hi> to be with a like commonneſs imparted for preſerving the <hi>Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet theſe kind of men (that lead Scripture captive) dare plead the <hi>Infallibility</hi> of their own Church; a word wherein <hi>the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Iniquity</hi> is ſum'd up, and from whence they have fetcht all their <hi>Artillery</hi> to beat down every thing that oppoſed them: which puts me in mind of that famous Engine <hi>Demetrius</hi> contriv'd, and is mentioned by <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his Life, that had ſeveral Rooms and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions in it to hold Souldiers; and the men that lodg'd there did fight with all ſorts of weapons. Such is
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41913:19"/>their <hi>Engine</hi> of an <hi>Infallible Guide;</hi> but certainly of it ſelf it would little prevail, were it not for its many <hi>Cells</hi> and the Forces that fill them. For behold! what Bands of <hi>Friers,</hi> what Companies of <hi>Prieſts</hi> lie there arm'd and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to defend their Cauſe! This word <hi>(Infallible)</hi> has ſtrength e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough with them to ſolve all Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments for <hi>Truth,</hi> to remove all objections againſt <hi>Error;</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all it ſo blinds their whole party, that they can neither diſcern any compounded mixtures in Faith, nor notorious ſcandals in practice; though the one proceeds from all the groſſneſs of <hi>Humane Invention,</hi> and the other from all the licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs of <hi>Corrupt Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the falſeneſs of that Title they pretend to, is ſufficiently laid open in the world; and they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too might be convinc'd of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41913:20"/>the arrogance of their claim; ſince what-ever promiſe they may plead for ſuch an aſſiſtance, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns only the <hi>leading</hi> of the <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church,</hi> and is limited too in its ſenſe to points <hi>neceſſary for its ſalvation;</hi> whereas they (being on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>part</hi> of that Body, and a part wretchedly <hi>fallen</hi> in Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples) cannot truly be ſaid to be upheld by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> but rather Judicially forſaken, by reaſon of their baniſhing the <hi>Word of Truth,</hi> which can only ſecure the Spirits Conduct. But I paſs from hence to the Second Aggravation of this ſin; wherein I ſhall conſider,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Motives that lead men to it.</p>
            <p>Could men urge ſome power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Temptation for the reaſon they had to hinder <hi>the Authority of Religion</hi> over them, they might fetch an excuſe from it; but when
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41913:20"/>a baſe luſt, a ſordid appetite ſhall get ſtrength to prevail, this height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens the Crime becauſe of the ſhamefulneſs of that Conqueſt. In all Irreligion we are poorly maſter'd, or rather betray'd. The Will quits its allegiance to the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding (which by nature it is a ſervant to) for a mean, narrow, ſhrunken object, that cannot ſo much as bribe it by a Reward. Atheiſm is built upon groſs di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of <hi>Senſe,</hi> and <hi>Luſt</hi> forms to its ſelf principles to reſiſt <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> wherein Man (pretending to live free) is left miſerably bound by his <hi>Slave.</hi> Conſult the whole Method of an Atheiſtical diſcourſe: In Fleſh it begins and ends with it; but take once out of Mans mind <hi>carnal Hopes,</hi> and <hi>ſenſual Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations,</hi> then the Soul comes to do it ſelf right, by being filled with proper Ideas of God and Eternity.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:41913:21"/>Devotion is the genuine birth of our Thoughts while the ſtreams of them are pure; but Impiety is a <hi>Monſter,</hi> that out of <hi>mud and ſtime</hi> is formed. We may know its O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal by its Fruits, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery of an Atheiſt's reaſon by his practice, whoſe love of Drink, Whoredom, Gluttony, and other foul Uncleanneſſes, furniſhes him with Arguments to defend them. Upon the ſame ſcore the Heathens maintain'd their Idol-Temples, becauſe their inclinations led them to vice, and the Gods of thoſe Temples ſhowed them the way.</p>
            <p>The like Reaſon may be given for that exact care and diligence in the <hi>Roman</hi>-Church to ſuppreſs Truth, which is <hi>Luſt</hi> and <hi>Intereſt.</hi> Theſe are the Two commanding Principles they are ſway'd by, and <hi>Unrighteouſneſs</hi> is ſerv'd by them for low wages. They hide
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41913:21"/>the true doctrine of a <hi>preſent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> that their followers may ſin all their life-time without fear, and at laſt purge by <hi>Confeſsion:</hi> They conceal the True Tenet of Chriſts <hi>full ſatisfaction</hi> (whereby both ſin and puniſhment are taken off) that they may make an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer</hi> of Mans Pardons: They deſtroy the nature of <hi>Good works,</hi> and make them to be nothing elſe but an <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Compounding:</hi> The <hi>Creature</hi> is ſet up by them (as it was by the <hi>Gentiles</hi>) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>beſides the Creator:</hi> They drive at <hi>Univerſal Empire</hi> and Soveraignty, and in order to this all <hi>worldly Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems</hi> are made uſe of; ſo that it is hard to judg whether their <hi>Capitol</hi> or their <hi>Church</hi> be better founded. A <hi>Mans Head</hi> (we know) did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominate the one, and I am ſure it lies at the <hi>Foundation</hi> of the other; except you'l ſay the <hi>Old Serpent</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:41913:22"/>gets in to help the <hi>Subtilty</hi> of it, and to mix his <hi>poyſon</hi> with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention. Indeed they may boaſt of their Politicks thus improv'd. But whoever will ſurvey the whole Model of their Religion, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially view their Diſcipline and Practice, he ſhall find Truth is hid by them for carnal ends, which adds new height to the ſin.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third and laſt aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is drawn from the effects that follow this violence offer'd to Truth.</p>
            <p>Whoever ſhall ſuppreſs the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Religion in himſelf, does thereby contract a hardneſs in his ſoul to commit iniquity, and lives a continued ſcandal to his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; but whoſoever ſhall ſuppreſs <hi>Truth</hi> by a Law, he thereby pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims his defiance of it, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployes all his force to ſix Error and Corruption in the World. How
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41913:22"/>can Injuſtice riſe higher than this caſe! for it is a <hi>flat war againſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> a <hi>publick Invaſion of each mans privilege;</hi> it is a <hi>digging of the Eyes</hi> out of that <hi>Head,</hi> which ſhould be <hi>general in its shine;</hi> and a reducing of things to a <hi>ſtrange Chaos;</hi> where the confuſion is far worſe (when Truth and Falſehood, Good and Evil are not known) than when Heaven and Earth lay undiſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. O how ſad and deplorable is Mens caſe, to be left in ignorance of their way to Eternal Happineſs! Who can poſſibly attain to Life without a knowledge of it before hand, or be brought <hi>from the power of Satan unto God,</hi> except their <hi>eyes be firſt opened,</hi> and their Spiritual Blindneſs removed? There is no altering of Gods Methods to ſave, nor of the courſe of his Spirit to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert men; who begins in an act of <hi>Conviction</hi> upon the Underſtanding,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41913:23"/>and conveys by it to the Will its <hi>ſanctifying operation;</hi> ſo that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>enlightning</hi> there can be no <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing</hi> of the inner man, and by conſequence no fitting or prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of him for Glory. So then look where Truth is hid, there ſo many ſouls are buried, and deſcend by degrees from one Gulf into an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. Till the Priſon be broke, and light again reſtored, a recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is impoſſible. Therefore when ſuch a <hi>General ruine</hi> is the iſſue of <hi>Religions Captivity,</hi> the crime of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it muſt needs be heinous, and ariſe in proportion to thoſe miſchiefs that are cauſed.</p>
            <p>I could alledg the ſame inſtance I before mentioned, as a pregnant proof to ſhew how deſtructive it is to a people that <hi>Truth</hi> ſhould be withheld, and an <hi>Inquiſition</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed to keep off that Tryal. Hence multitudes periſh for lack
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41913:23"/>of Knowledg, and wanting a requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Faith (which a blind Credulity takes the place of) are in all the folly of it condemn'd. But <hi>light</hi> they pretend wounds men, and Scripture (if publick) deceives, many wreſting it to their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; a liberty (ſay they) of Chriſtian knowledg is but a Curſe and a <hi>rank Field</hi> for ſeveral <hi>Hereſies</hi> to ſpring up; whence it is better to root it out, and thereby hinder the growth of tares. But an Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this kind is eaſily anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: for there was never any thing of great eſteem and uſe for mans Life, but it bred a difference in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. As Phyſick intended for the cure of Bodies, and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy for the health of Souls, are both fruitful of many queſtions; yet none in his wits would avoid Phyſick or Philoſophy, becauſe of <hi>different Sects and Parties</hi> they breed;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41913:24"/>ſo neither ſhould <hi>the free uſe of Scripture</hi> be condemned, in regard of <hi>differences</hi> amongſt men; which proceed not ſo much from their ſtudy of contention, as from a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety in their abilities to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. Farther, were this charge of theirs valid to null the force of the rule, let then the great <hi>Eye</hi> of the <hi>Firmament</hi> be pulled out, becauſe he raiſes <hi>vapours</hi> as well as <hi>enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens:</hi> The <hi>vapours</hi> that are rais'd he owes to the <hi>Earth,</hi> but <hi>enlightning</hi> muſt be aſcrib'd to <hi>his own Body.</hi> Would we certainly know the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the Goſpel is hid? It is jealouſie and fear of being refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: An evil eye will not bear Light, nor a diſeaſed Conſcience retain it: Light reproves and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces where it comes; for this cauſe they keep it cloſe, dealing with Truth as the <hi>Tyrians</hi> did with their God, whom they fetter'd
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41913:24"/>with a ſtrong <hi>Chain,</hi> leſt (if free) he ſhould leave their <hi>City,</hi> and take the <hi>Enemies ſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto I have ſpoken of the <hi>Charge;</hi> whoſe greatneſs does ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from the treaſon that is in the Act, from the baſeneſs of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and from the murdering na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the effects: proceed we to ſpeak a little of the juſtneſs of the <hi>Sentence</hi> that is here denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe who hold the Truth in Unrighteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>It may perhaps be counted a diſproportionable reward by ſome, that wicked mens <hi>finite Acts</hi> ſhould be <hi>everlaſtingly</hi> puniſhed: But did they farther regard them as <hi>Acts of Strength</hi> where the <hi>Will governs, Acts of Enmity</hi> where <hi>Revelation is oppoſ'd,</hi> they would not ſo readily complain of the <hi>rigour</hi> of that Judgment. Beſides there is an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity for ſuch a <hi>Sentence</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:41913:25"/>to ſecure Religion in the World, ſince the bounds of Chriſtianity would be quickly paſt over, were not <hi>infinite terrors</hi> the fence to keep Travellers in. And what ſeems more loudly to call for it, than the ſin I have already diſcourſ'd of? or how ſhall the authority of Truth be maintain'd, the honour of God vindicated, and the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries done to our Brethren aveng'd, but by ſo ſignal a puniſhment? Take thy meaſures of the offence from the Object: in that Glaſs thou mayſt diſcern its full ſtature. He that quenches <hi>Light;</hi> ſtrives to deſtroy the God of it; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo high a provocation, the ſame God is ſollicited to exerciſe his Omnipotence in a revenge. The Princes of this World would be ſatisfied to the utmoſt, when their Subjects daringly rebel; only their want of power cauſes a weakneſs
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41913:25"/>in their blows: God that can take the extremity of a payment when an affront is offer'd him, purſues but the will of a Soveraign in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo.</p>
            <p>Did he indeed hide Truth from us, we might likewiſe be hid from his Juſtice: but when he clearly propounds it to us, and enables our Wills to cloſe with it, here we inexcuſably offend. Now we ſay <hi>we ſee,</hi> therefore <hi>our ſin remains;</hi> now we confeſs we are aſſiſted by Heaven, therefore Heaven is <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd</hi> when it puniſhes. May we not with ſhame own that reproof which God delivered againſt <hi>Iſrael, Your deſtruction is of your ſelves?</hi> May we not apply what he had ſpoken againſt <hi>Jeruſalem, What could have been done more for my Vineyard that was not done?</hi> For he has taught us by his <hi>Word,</hi> awakened us by his <hi>Rod,</hi> invited us by his <hi>Bounty,</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41913:26"/>himſelf to us by his <hi>Grace,</hi> while we deſperately forſake our own mercy. Even the worſt of men taſte of his Goodneſs; They find his Spirit in their <hi>Conſciences</hi> to check, in their <hi>Minds</hi> to guide, in their <hi>Wills</hi> to allure them; he wooes, he ſollicits, he waits, all our Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties he beſets, that he might draw us over to the Government of his Laws. He is always free and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municative of his Treaſures, but it is mans guilt cuts off the ſpring. Tax not then the Method of Gods proceedings, that ſummons into an extraordinary Court the groſs abuſer of his Talents; but reflect ſadly upon the ſinfulneſs of thine own ways, that cauſes <hi>Grace</hi> to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter its <hi>ſhape,</hi> and the <hi>face</hi> of a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> to be <hi>transfigur'd</hi> with <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall cloſe this point with an Inference from the whole.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:41913:26"/>
            <p>I ſuppoſe none will expect in this place I ſhould attempt a deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Divine Wrath,</hi> which though it be revealed from Heaven, is yet hid in the manner of execution. So <hi>Lightning</hi> is diſcerned by its <hi>bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> when it ſtrikes, though the way of its working is not ſeen. How the <hi>Fire</hi> below by an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty breath will be kindled, and yet kept by the ſame breath from conſuming the Sinner, it is not for us to explain; but certainly the Wound, the Smart, the Plague is intolerable, where-ever the weight of Gods Juſtice falls. And they of all men will feel its burden, that bring Light to their puniſhment; whereby they are forced to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the <hi>double calamity</hi> they are preſt with, namely <hi>Wrath</hi> not to be <hi>ſhunn'd,</hi> and <hi>Sin</hi> not to be <hi>pleaded for.</hi> Here the <hi>Sword</hi> cuts deep, enters the very marrow and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41913:27"/>ſpirits, and <hi>renews</hi> continually its <hi>edge with piercing.</hi> Who is able to meet Vengeance in its aſſaults, and Light in its convictions? Is not their force ſtrong, nay irreſiſtible where they come? Behold! the one <hi>makes,</hi> and the other <hi>quickens</hi> our Hell; the one <hi>binds</hi> us faſt, and the other <hi>heats</hi> our Furnace.</p>
            <p>I know the Theme I now inſiſt on is not ſuited to a Scoffers ear, becauſe not ſuited to his deſigns. What have we to do (ſays an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure) with a warning of Gods Juſtice, that chaſtiſes all our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, and mingles gall with our pleaſures? If Religion muſt be preached up, let Grace and Mercy be revealed: Thoſe have a healing quality in them, and like <hi>Beds of ſpices</hi> refreſh with their <hi>opening;</hi> but Treaſures of Wrath, and the Pains of another World, theſe like <hi>noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome pits</hi> do puniſh us in our <hi>ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:41913:27"/>Thus he would ſecure his way of ſinning to himſelf, and remove all ſting from his conſcience.</p>
            <p>But alas! his arts are in vain; were he freed from any outward ſounds of the Miniſtry of the Word, yet his mind is ſtill checked with a future Judgment, and by fits ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits to the Revelation. Indeed how can it be otherwiſe? for the notions of God and his Juſtice are twiſted together in our Souls; and the ſame impreſſion that convinces us of his Being, convinces us too of his Wrath againſt ſin: nothing remains but that the eternity of it appear, and when that is effected, the Soul neceſſarily yields, and witneſſes its ſurrender by thoſe pungent acts of reflecting.</p>
            <p>We ſuppoſe now adayes <hi>Atheiſm</hi> to abound, and fortifie that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition by our frequent diſcourſes to confute it; but if there be ſuch
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41913:28"/>a <hi>Leproſie</hi> amongſt Chriſtians, it does not ſo much ſeize the <hi>head</hi> as the <hi>heart,</hi> which is the <hi>ſeat</hi> of the <hi>Devils Diſeaſe;</hi> and he cares not to ſpread it farther in his Children. All our crime is, not that Divine Characters in us are loſt, but only hid in our ſouls: Truth we bury by our practice, though we feel it lives to our torment. And God grant we be not puniſhed for our Ingratitude with outward darkneſs by a removal of his Candleſtick from amongſt us. Do we now pride our ſelves in this, that we enjoy mercy? but let us alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the dangerous neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Vindictive Juſtice, when that Mercy is deſpiſ'd. What At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute is there can reſcue us from the ſtroke, when Goodneſs will not defend? Is it <hi>Power</hi> we may flee to? but that determines it ſelf to deſtroy: Is it <hi>Wiſdom?</hi> but that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41913:28"/>contrives the way of deſtroying: Is it <hi>Holineſs?</hi> but that juſtifies the proceeding; whence <hi>Goodneſs</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is the ſecurity of the Sinner: That <hi>Altar of Refuge</hi> God himſelf has ſet up to ſtop the courſe of his own Vengeance. And yet even here we are not ſafe, becauſe our abuſe forfeits the Privilege; all the protection of it is loſt through our ſtubbornneſs of offending; whereby we become guilty of a <hi>mad Sacrilege,</hi> when we pull down the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> that might ſave us. There is no ſin ſo aggravating as what ſtrikes at God in an <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical</hi> Revelation: for here we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend againſt his <hi>laſt</hi> and <hi>beſt</hi> method of drawing us to him.</p>
            <p>You are all diggers in <hi>Truths Mine,</hi> and have your toyl paid with thoſe pleaſures you find there; but where ought it to be ſeen in its greateſt beauty, if not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41913:29"/>amongſt thoſe that chiefly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it? All kind of <hi>Truth</hi> has <hi>charms</hi> upon its <hi>face</hi> to get Lovers, but the <hi>Truth of Religion</hi> has a <hi>Divine Image</hi> upon it to win Souls, and an <hi>Eternal Dowry</hi> to hold them: Blind are we if we reſiſt, abſurd if we refuſe ſuch a Temptation. The Duty I here preſs is very ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable; for the Object you ſee deſerves Love, ay and the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of Love to purſue it. How can Luſts or Fears take room in a Chriſtian, that has ſuch high Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to govern him! Propound to thy ſelf <hi>Good and Evil</hi> in their full latitude here; ſwell them to their biggeſt bulk; dreſs them in their choiceſt colours and ſhows, they ſink to nothing with a religious compariſon: Heaven melts away all the <hi>paint</hi> of a <hi>preſent delight,</hi> and Hell renders all the <hi>Vizards</hi> of <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward danger</hi> contemptible; ſo that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41913:29"/>neither the one, nor the other, can ſtir a paſſion in the Soul when our thoughts are well planted.</p>
            <p>Therefore if either the Mercy of a God can move, or the Wrath of Almighty can bind us; if the Scepter of Grace can perſwade, or the Lightning of Juſtice terrifie, if Life, if Death be of any moment to us, let us be faſt maintainers of the <hi>Truth,</hi> and commend our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to the world by that <hi>Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible</hi> ſtamp of our lives.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:41913:30"/>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:41913:30"/>
            <head>The Second Diſcourſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Cor. 7.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Having therefore theſe Promiſes, let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs both of Fleſh and Spirit, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting Holineſs in the Fear of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the laſt verſe of the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Chapter (to which theſe words chiefly refer) we find what a gracious promiſe God makes to his People, when He aſſures them (if they ſeparate from ſin) in what a glorious manner He will receive them; allowing them the nobleſt Privilege a Creature can have, and the beſt ſecurity to maintain it. For the Promiſe runs
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:41913:31"/>thus, <hi>I will be a Father unto you, and ye ſhall be my Sons and Daughters, ſaith the Lord Almighty</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the former of theſe Titles ſpeaks not only the <hi>nearneſs</hi> of our <hi>Creator,</hi> but all the <hi>bounty</hi> of his <hi>Grace:</hi> the latter declares not only a <hi>height</hi> our <hi>Natures</hi> are raiſ'd to, but an equal <hi>advancement</hi> of our <hi>Hopes;</hi> and the <hi>Lord Almighty</hi> (ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the cloſe) is the beſt <hi>Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> againſt <hi>Fear,</hi> ſince a <hi>Father</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming it to himſelf, does thereby direct its influence to ſave us.</p>
            <p>I grant <hi>Power</hi> to be dreadful of it ſelf, and <hi>Omnipotence</hi> much more; but let the name of <hi>Mercy</hi> be joynd, all the pleaſantneſs of its luſtre is caſt on it: we can then view it as a <hi>calm Sea,</hi> where breadth and depth grow delightful, by reaſon of the gentleneſs of the Current: ſo when an <hi>Almighty Lord</hi> confirms this to us, that He will treat us
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:41913:31"/>like <hi>Sons,</hi> we can then chearfully contemplate the Attribute of his Greatneſs, becauſe all the Majeſty of it is allayed with his condeſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing goodneſs to Mankind. This then being every-where offered in the Goſpel (that perfect Model of Divine love) what is the Fruit we ſhould return to our God, but ſuch a work of obedience that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares and fits us for what is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed; that ſtamps upon us Gods Image in our Souls, and conveys with that Stamp our right to Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? <hi>Having therefore theſe Promiſes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We may obſerve in the words three particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Motive.</item>
               <item>2. A Duty.</item>
               <item>3. The Manner of perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Motive anſwers our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt deſires; for it conſiſts of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Promiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:41913:32"/>
            <p>The Duty contains the beſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratives; for it lies in purifying of <hi>Fleſh and Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, The Manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming it affords the ſureſt marks to undeceive us; for it is a <hi>Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of Holineſs in Gods Fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt <hi>perſwades,</hi> the Second <hi>qualifies,</hi> and the Third <hi>diſtinguiſhes</hi> our Religion from the Worlds.</p>
            <p>I begin with the <hi>Motive,</hi> as it powerfully perſwades to Chriſtian Practice: <hi>Having therefore theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi> — Where we may note by the way, how allowable it is in our Chriſtian Profeſſion to regard the Titles and Privileges of it for the better encouragement of our ſervice. It is not a <hi>mercenary,</hi> but a <hi>rational</hi> act to eye a reward in any action we perform; much more the reward of eternal Bleſſedneſs; ſince the very <hi>End of our Faith</hi> (with St. <hi>Peter</hi>) is the <hi>Salvation of our Souls.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41913:32"/>Moſes</hi> (the greateſt Prophet of the Jews, and a Type of our Lord Chriſt) had a reſpect to the <hi>recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence</hi> of reward; and this our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> commands us in another place to <hi>run that we may obtain:</hi> ſo that to bid us do Gods Commandments meerly for the Beauty of Holineſs which is in them, without looking upon the Promiſes for our ſupport, is to make all our Religion a poor thin Speculation, when it affords us no proſpect; and to turn our Obedience into an uncomfortable ſlavery, by cutting off thoſe helps the Goſpel propounds for our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion.</p>
            <p>But for the better handling of the Motive (here layd down) I ſhall conſider Two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Nature of Mans will that is to be moved.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The fitneſs of Gods Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to inflame it.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:41913:33"/>
            <p n="1">1. For the nature of mans Will; How <hi>free</hi> ſoever it be in its acting, yet it has always Good for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of its choice; nor can Evil (as ſuch) be poſſibly deſired. Nay, it is Truth of Good Man properly ſeeks; but that Appearances and Colours ſhould more often allure us, it is rather the effect of error and weakneſs, than the genuine product of our Wills. As the <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding</hi> affects what ought to be <hi>known,</hi> ſo the <hi>Will</hi> affects what ought to be <hi>coveted;</hi> only the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual part in us over-rules, that ſtops the one in its proper purſuit, and ſpoils the motion of the other.</p>
            <p>We all find in our ſelves, how earneſtly we deſire ſome <hi>chief Good,</hi> and therefore preſently cloſe with Happineſs propoſed; but if this Happineſs be inquir'd into what it is, then indeed we fall off and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide; which arriſes from the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptneſs
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:41913:33"/>of mens affections, that inclining them ſeveral ways, teach them to ſet up ſeveral Objects, where they wretchedly wander and turn aſide, and ſo miſs of that which in the general notion they ſeek after. Yet for all this the Will of Man as it follows Reaſon (for ſo it differs from <hi>Appetite</hi>) is diſpoſed by it to follow the beſt grounds, and allow particularly of that Good which does moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to its perfection.</p>
            <p>And ſo I proceed to ſhow in the ſecond place.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The fitneſs of Gods Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to inflame Mans Will.</p>
            <p>This will appear in that they contain all thoſe Topicks of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion that can poſſibly belong to any Promiſe: ſuch are <hi>Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> of <hi>Good, Infallibility of Obtaining,</hi> and a <hi>Miſerable defect</hi> as to both theſe in any <hi>other offer</hi> beſides.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:41913:34"/>
            <p>Now we need not prove in the Firſt place the <hi>intrinſick Excellency</hi> of what is <hi>promiſed,</hi> ſince that rich offer of <hi>Adoption</hi> includes in it what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Gift an All-ſufficient Being can beſtow. For hereby we are tranſlated into Gods own Family, and inveſted with ſuitable Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges as his Children. All things are here allowed us that can be hoped for from a <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Love,</hi> and from a <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Power;</hi> which combining together their <hi>proper acts,</hi> compleat the Riches of a Chriſtians Inheritance. In the Old Teſtament <hi>Father</hi> is not a name that God was ſtyl'd by, but onely <hi>Lord;</hi> and the Title the Jews had was that of a <hi>Servant:</hi> which though it take honour from their relation to ſuch a Maſter, yet it imports in it ſelf all the <hi>Burden</hi> of Duty: But in the New, where <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Lord</hi> are both joyn'd,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41913:34"/>and to become <hi>Sons and Daughters,</hi> is the Privilege of his People; this ſpeaks at once the <hi>Eaſe</hi> of their Service, and the <hi>Comfort</hi> of their Hopes as to a <hi>future enjoying.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed God ſhews in this Covenant of Grace his utmoſt contrivance to draw us to him. As it was the <hi>Conſultation</hi> of his <hi>Wiſdom</hi> at firſt to <hi>make,</hi> ſo it is here the <hi>labour</hi> of his <hi>Love</hi> to <hi>invite</hi> us; for which end He reveals his Treaſures, opens his Stores, ſets out Heaven in its <hi>chief Lights;</hi> any, converts himſelf to a Reward. He deſired <hi>emptineſs</hi> to become Man, that He might take again <hi>fulneſs</hi> to enrich him. Is it then Life, Joy, Liberty, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or any other Good we count excellent? Behold! the Purchaſe of it by him who propounds to us theſe bleſſings; and having alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>widened</hi> our <hi>Faculties</hi> for <hi>deſire,</hi> He farther <hi>enables</hi> our <hi>Natures</hi> to <hi>receive.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:41913:35"/>
            <p>Next let us regard the <hi>Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Obtaining,</hi> which cannot but render a Promiſe as exceeding worthy to be prized.</p>
            <p>The worth and excellency of any Good is a ſure foundation of our eſteem; but our certainty of having it is that which fixes our Love, and crowns our Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in purſuing it. Now this certainty of ours, as to what God promiſes, is built upon two great Attributes, <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotence;</hi> which are like But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes to ſupport our <hi>Faith</hi> and our <hi>Hope;</hi> the one freeing us from all jealouſies of a <hi>deceit,</hi> the other from all dread of a <hi>diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</hi> How can we diſtruſt or fear Gods failing us, that is every way qualified to ſave! Firſt, the Covenant He makes is fram'd by his <hi>Love;</hi> then <hi>Truth</hi> writes it down; afterwards <hi>Power</hi> comes in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41913:35"/>to ſeal up the Aſſurance; ſo that no room is left for any doubt or ſcruple, ſince all his Promiſes are ſure; nor will Mans expectation ever ſhame him, if <hi>Sin</hi> does not, the onely <hi>blot</hi> of our <hi>hopes,</hi> as well as the <hi>ſtain</hi> of our <hi>pleaſures.</hi> Nothing but Sin can poſſibly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat us: it is Sin which under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines all our Bleſſings, alters our claim and property in Bliſs, and gives the <hi>Threatnings</hi> in Scripture Authority to <hi>ſucceed. In him the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are Yea and Amen,</hi> that is, firm and ſtedfaſt: and when we fall off by a wilfull Apoſtacy, their <hi>ſtedfaſtneſs</hi> ſtill remains in their own <hi>nature;</hi> only the benefit of <hi>Application</hi> is loſt to Us. But if we once turn to our God by a true Repentance, if we approve our worſhip of him by the ſincerity of our hearts, and the <hi>holineſs</hi> of our lives, lo! they are firm and <hi>ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41913:36"/>to us</hi> alſo: God cannot in that caſe exclude us from Heaven; for we bring him the condition of happineſs he requires from us; we produce the <hi>Grace</hi> that leads thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and know it is impoſſible He ſhould either deny his own terms, or refuſe the likeneſs of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing to be conſidered in Gods Promiſes, is, That He has provided againſt all Temptations from <hi>other offers,</hi> by diſperſing a <hi>Vacuum</hi> in things, and leaving no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing here below fit to ſtir or move us, except you'l ſay <hi>defect of Subſtance,</hi> and <hi>want of Certainty</hi> are charms. Were any Good up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth adequate to our ſouls, had it worth and certainty to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract our deſires, then I grant we might juſtifie the <hi>byas</hi> of our incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations that way; becauſe the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fibleneſs of what is offer'd us is a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41913:36"/>farther motive to <hi>turn</hi> them thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but when <hi>vanity,</hi> nay, <hi>vanity of vanities</hi> is <hi>ſuperſcrib'd</hi> upon all the Creation, here is not the leaſt colour for our adherence. What is there I pray in this World can be exhibited to us, but ſome <hi>Scenes</hi> of Good, and <hi>Images</hi> of an Inheritance? Thus Chriſt by the Great <hi>Tempter</hi> was entertained with <hi>Landskips and Shows,</hi> and Kingdoms that were drawn in <hi>Airy Figures,</hi> where the <hi>Delight</hi> could not recompence the <hi>Emptineſs</hi> of the <hi>Proſpect.</hi> The like emptineſs is ſpread through every thing here; and for any one to reckon upon a ſetled Poſſeſſion, it is like caſting <hi>anchor</hi> upon a <hi>wave,</hi> or binding the <hi>wheels</hi> of <hi>Times mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> In a word, ſuch a Task that has an impoſſibility in the Act to baffle the Deſign. But where the Promiſes are of God there is <hi>weight and ſtedfaſtneſs</hi> to perſwade us:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41913:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:41913:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:41913:38"/>weight that can fix all the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancy of deſire, and ſtedfaſtneſs ſtrengthen our patience of expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Thus you ſee the force of the <hi>Motive</hi> to confirm that Inference he makes from it.</p>
            <p>I proceed now to handle in the ſecond place.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Duty</hi> which contains in it the beſt Preparations for receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe <hi>Promiſes: Let us cleanſe our ſelves from all Filthineſs both of Fleſh and Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where we may take notice,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the Act, <hi>Cleanſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Of the Subject about which it is employ'd, <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> that is Body and Soul; ſo that a thorough <hi>Baptiſm of the whole man</hi> is required; and ſuch a waſhing in the Fountain of Repentance that purges away inward and outward defilements.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:41913:38"/>
            <p n="1">1. The Act is remarkable, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Let us cleanſe:</hi> a <hi>word</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Heathen Schools by way of Speculation, but preſcribed to the Jewiſh and Chriſtian Church as a rule of Practice.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Heathens</hi> were not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant of it, when they ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Vertue</hi> it ſelf to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Cleanſing;</hi> which the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> give us this account of, namely, That it is a retirement of the Soul within, and a ſeparating from the Body in its motions, when Reaſon acts freely and undiſturbedly, nor has any tincture from the Paſſions to defile it: ſuch a ſtate ſay they of the Soul is <hi>pure and divine.</hi> This I confeſs may in ſome ſort be call'd a <hi>Purgation,</hi> but it is very defective in another ſenſe, where they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe no guilt to be waſhed off, which both Soul and Body have contracted: They regard onely a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:41913:39"/>
               <hi>refining</hi> of the <hi>Intellectual Powers,</hi> but ſeek no <hi>purifying</hi> of any <hi>ſinfull uncleanneſs.</hi> And this muſt be chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imputed to that natural <hi>pride</hi> they all had, that they would not allow of a <hi>corrupt ſpring;</hi> as we muſt owe it wholly to their <hi>am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition,</hi> that they ſtudied to advance <hi>Reaſon</hi> in its actings; therefore the <hi>Fountain of ſin</hi> being unſearch'd, we cannot admit them for Judges here; but ought to conſult the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> for the true notion of <hi>Cleanſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Jewiſh Church</hi> the outward Ceremony was enjoyn'd, but withal Typical of the <hi>inward:</hi> whence we read in <hi>Exodus</hi> of an expreſs Command before the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of the Law, That they ſhould <hi>ſanctifie themſelves and waſh their cloaths;</hi> from which Precept their Doctors gather that Tenet and Cuſtome they had for <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:41913:39"/>all whom they admitted to their <hi>Church and Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that they ſhould thus be <hi>waſh'd</hi> in order to receive the <hi>Law</hi> that was publiſhed, it argued both a greatneſs of guilt in the parties, and an abſolute neceſſity of repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when not ſo much as a ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Garment was allowed to be near that Mount that quaked and trembled; leſt the Lightnings of the place ſhould break forth to conſume, and the Trumpet (there heard) proclaim nothing but Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. If ſuch a preparation were requiſite for <hi>hearing</hi> Gods Will, much more was it for <hi>obeying:</hi> whence thoſe Sacrifices of old (He commanded) were firſt to derive their <hi>cleanneſs</hi> from the <hi>Offerer,</hi> and ſo had their force of <hi>Legal Attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Were the Offerer not <hi>ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> beforehand, all his Worſhip was ſpoil'd by reaſon of the ſpots
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:41913:40"/>and blemiſhes that overſpread it: The <hi>foulneſs</hi> of his hand laid a <hi>Curſe</hi> upon the <hi>Expiation,</hi> and by ſlaying the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> he deſtroy'd the <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi> Therefore a ſtrict way of Cleanſing was obſerv'd in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, whereby God led them to the Spiritual Duty; as he taught them by Temporary Promiſes to have a taſte and relliſh of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly. And leſt they ſhould at any time forget what was ſignified, their <hi>Purifyings</hi> were <hi>frequently</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated on them: repreſenting to them in the ſame waſhing <hi>New Guilt,</hi> and a <hi>New Obligation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Chriſtian Purifying is of a higher nature, as being <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly</hi> but <hi>once;</hi> to ſhew <hi>We are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with Chriſt by Baptiſm into Death, that like-as He was rais'd from the Glory of the Father, even ſo we alſo ſhould walk in newneſs of Life.</hi> Here is no need of ſprinkling Garments,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:41913:40"/>and Veſſels, nor of ſeparating from the Camp upon an Uncleanneſs, when the whole work of Holineſs is fully exhibited, and one ſolemn Rite introduces the performance.</p>
            <p>The work divides it ſelf into two parts, according to the diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mans nature, whereof the firſt is</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A cleanſing from the Filthineſs of the Fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And good reaſon is there to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with it: For though <hi>Sin</hi> be properly the <hi>Souls act,</hi> yet by the <hi>Body</hi> it firſt appears; nay, this Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of ours, being joyned with the Soul, becomes rather a <hi>Miniſter</hi> than an <hi>Inſtrument</hi> in its working; ſuch a Miniſter that continually provides fewel for the <hi>Hearts luſts,</hi> and makes the corruption of them viſible to the world. If then the <hi>Murdering Sword</hi> be juſtly caſt off, and the <hi>Cup broke</hi> whereby the man
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41913:41"/>hath been <hi>poyſon'd,</hi> how much more ought this <hi>Principle of Fleſh</hi> to be cleanſed and ſubdued, that ſo deeply ſhares in the Souls guilt, and proves an <hi>active Executioner</hi> in it ruine! I need not mention the ſeveral <hi>works</hi> of it, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle tells us <hi>are manifeſt,</hi> becauſe they diſcover themſelves with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtains and inward impreſſions upon the conſciences of men. Thoſe acts of the <hi>outward man,</hi> that expreſs themſelves in worſhipping an Idol, in Murder, Sacrilege, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellings, Laſciviouſneſs and the like, pollute the <hi>Body</hi> that commits them, and convey farther the taint of that pollution to the <hi>Soul.</hi> Nor can Men with all their art ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and diſgrace what is convey'd there, as that the nature of its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity ſhould be changed; but the <hi>Corruptions of Fleſh</hi> will ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide <hi>frightful</hi> even in the midſt of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41913:41"/>their <hi>Conqueſt.</hi> Sin then carrying its own Conviction, the great Query is, How we ſhould purge it? But to this the Aſſiſtance of Grace, and Mans Reſolution is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: the former will not fail if the latter be preſent; nor will the latter be wanting if Gods <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi> be the <hi>Object.</hi> Where <hi>theſe</hi> are ſtedfaſtly beheld, they will ſurely melt and diſſolve us, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully break our rocky hearts, and engage us anew in a Life of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goodneſs</hi> is commanding in its own nature, and <hi>enthrones</hi> it ſelf in Mans Will; nor needs it other force for keeping its <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> but what it continually carries by <hi>charming</hi> the <hi>affections.</hi> And this Goodneſs is fully ſeen in Gods <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes:</hi> all the <hi>Vail</hi> is taken off, which is generally caſt upon Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; and inſtead of glimpſes
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41913:42"/>and <hi>half-lights</hi> we are allowed a full diſcovery of their glory; ſuch a one in its working that can joyn <hi>ſurprize, delight</hi> and <hi>victory</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. For all the Graces of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour are here ſhown, and al the Riches of Eternity are here mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted; which muſt needs take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the reſiſtance of <hi>Fleſh,</hi> provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded we be fixt in our Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Why then are we not ſerious in weighing theſe things? why does not Love, nor Mercy conſtrain us? I am ſure no carnal Temptation can be endued with ſuch ſtrength: It is ſeated in <hi>Fleſh,</hi> which is <hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and only conquers that Heart which is unprepar'd. The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion that was put to <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> when he had in his head the deſign of conquering many Kingdoms, may be put to the purſuers of Sin in thoſe various <hi>forms</hi> and <hi>faſhions of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:41913:42"/>Appetite,</hi> what it is they intend by all the Travel they make through a World of Corruption. Perhaps they will ſay (as he did, when we have compaſſed our deſigns we will the be quiet, and live to our ſelves: but to this the reply is ſtrong and forcible; why will they not be quiet now, and live to themſelves in a ſervice of their God, when that knowledge of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil they ſeek after is purchaſed with trouble, and manifeſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of their Souls? Therefore whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we would conſult our own Intereſt, or witneſs our Gratitude to God for his Promiſes, we are bound to be reſolute and ſpeedy in the <hi>cleanſing</hi> of this <hi>Fleſh,</hi> which at the beſt is but a <hi>burden,</hi> and ſin gives it a farther <hi>weight</hi> to cruſh and deſtroy us.</p>
            <p>But that we may perform this <hi>Duty</hi> aright, Two Rules are to be
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:41913:43"/>obſerved by us, which are here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated in my Text.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Object of our cleanſing be <hi>all. Filthineſs of the Fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That the work which refers to it, be ſo effectual, as that no <hi>Filthineſs</hi> ſhould return.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe is neceſſary, becauſe indeed without it there is no <hi>cleanſing;</hi> for wherever Filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is but in <hi>part</hi> waſhed off, the <hi>whole</hi> is ſtill denominated impure. Who will call that Body ſound, where the diſeaſe ſhifts places, but is not altogether removed? No more can we call that <hi>Fleſh cleans'd,</hi> where Vice changes its ſeat, but never loſes its commanding pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. It is true an Hypocrite may look fair in the worlds eye after a ſuperficial purging of ſome cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; but that cheat he puts upon others alters not the unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:41913:43"/>of his own temper. The Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of things remain fixt how changeable ſoever be mens Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. It is ſaid of <hi>Myriam</hi> the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> that ſhe appeared <hi>white as ſnow;</hi> but none could conclude from that <hi>whiteneſs</hi> any thing, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the malignancy of her <hi>diſeaſe;</hi> where the <hi>maſs</hi> of <hi>blood</hi> being taint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Body became wan and pale like a <hi>Dead Carcaſe.</hi> Such is the <hi>whiteneſs</hi> of ſome Profeſſors in thoſe half-acts of outward Purity; It is but a <hi>Leprous Hypocriſie,</hi> which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues <hi>deadneſs</hi> and <hi>rottenneſs</hi> within. But in Gods and Scripture account none are truly <hi>clean</hi> in the outward man, but thoſe that purge out eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing which defiles it: in whom the <hi>health</hi> and <hi>complexion</hi> is found by a <hi>vigorous</hi> expelling of all corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In theſe the Spirit truly worketh; and they ſhow their ſanctifying <hi>Principle</hi> to rule in them
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:41913:44"/>by an univerſal effect that follows it: For thus Gods Spirit acts in Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, diffuſing its vertue through all parts, nor can any deed paſs it uncleanſed: But when men ſolely act by their own ſpirit (which has a partial influence) then they ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle out ſome <hi>enormous Vice,</hi> ſome <hi>provoking Goliah</hi> to kill; which were a happy Conqueſt, did it make an impreſſion upon the groſs of an <hi>Army;</hi> but alas! here exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution is done, and not at all fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with any weakning in the <hi>Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, the ſecond is neceſſary, becauſe a <hi>Relapſe</hi> into <hi>Filth</hi> ſpoils the fruit of the former <hi>cleanſing,</hi> and withal doubles the <hi>ſtain.</hi> Therefore to prevent a guilt of that kind in this <hi>Body of fleſh,</hi> it muſt be our <hi>continued work</hi> to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due it: The only way to aſſure us of <hi>Sins Death,</hi> is by perſevering to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:41913:44"/>deſtroy its Dominion: that <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> within muſt be continually <hi>ſhav'd;</hi> nay the razor muſt pierce deep to the very <hi>roots,</hi> otherwiſe his <hi>ſtrength is not gone.</hi> Little ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities upon a remorſe are no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than a Drunkards ſoberneſs in his <hi>qualms;</hi> which he then <hi>dies to,</hi> but not to his <hi>ſin:</hi> ſhort penances upon check are but an Adulterers <hi>Whip,</hi> whereby he lets out <hi>Blood</hi> to cool a preſent <hi>Burning,</hi> but not to end the <hi>Diſeaſe.</hi> O the Art of a Profeſſor in thus ſubduing his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal motions; when he chooſes for a while the method of Rigour, only to give him eaſe in new ſins! Many can turn <hi>Hermits</hi> that way; with whom a ſuſpence of their luſt is but a preparative to freſh vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour: they endure much to ſin more; and make uſe of hardſhip to become helpful to their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, as Froſts and Snows are
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41913:45"/>to Seed; which they ſeem to lock up and bury in the ground, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed improve it for multiplying. If this be a <hi>cleanſing from all filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the fleſh,</hi> then let them that ſtudy an increaſe of their luſt be ſtyl'd the only Champions to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come it. But wouldſt thou have the true glory of it? then deny thy ſelf conſtantly in a Temptation, and hold out to the laſt in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of Repentance: So this Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Sin will appear utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated when thou bringeſt Time as a witneſs of thy <hi>Victory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there remains in the ſecond place another ſort of <hi>cleanſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>From all filthineſs of the Spirit.</hi> This is not ſo much conſidered in the world; but ſurely there is in ſome reſpects more of ſin, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently more of defilement than in Carnal corruption. Such are thoſe inward ſpots, of Pride, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41913:45"/>Envy, Hypocriſie, Diſtruſt of God; to conclude, all thoſe ſinful motions which it is proper for <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> to be guilty of.</p>
            <p>The Enormity of them will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear upon Three accounts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that they are the <hi>ſpring</hi> of all <hi>outward filthineſs.</hi> For from the <hi>Heart</hi> it is (or the <hi>ſpiritual part</hi> in man) that Fornication, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Blaſphemy flow; whence if theſe and the like ſins have all the foulneſs of tincture on them, the <hi>Sink</hi> whence they iſſue muſt be much more defil'd. Were evil Thoughts effectually reſtrain'd in us, all the ſtream of carnal wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs would be cut off; which made <hi>Solomon</hi> call for our greateſt care over the Heart, where ſinful Imaginations are cheriſhed. <hi>Keep thy heart</hi> (ſays he) <hi>with all diligence; for out of it are the Iſſues of Life;</hi> ay and of <hi>Death too</hi> when it is not
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:41913:46"/>rightly govern'd in its motions. An evil Heart makes an adulterous Eye, a deceitful Tongue, a violent Hand: All outward crimes are the Offſpring of the Thoughts; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>theſe</hi> (being the <hi>Parent-ſins</hi>) are the more aggravated in their guilt, as the <hi>cauſe</hi> of <hi>others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In that they are <hi>purely</hi> the <hi>Souls work,</hi> and that in its <hi>ſtrength,</hi> without the dregs of matter, or the weakneſs of fleſh to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid to <hi>Reuben, Thou art my Firſt-born, my might, and the beginning of my ſtrength, the excellency of dignity, and the excellency of power,</hi> the ſame may be applied to thoſe actions which <hi>primarily</hi> iſſue from the <hi>Soul.</hi> And ſo when they prove ſinful, they derive from the <hi>Dignity</hi> of thoſe noble faculties the greater <hi>ſhame.</hi> It is the Devils way thus to offend; and howſoever he may
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41913:46"/>tempt us to <hi>deeds of Fleſh,</hi> yet he is as to himſelf only an Agent in ſuch ſins that pollute the <hi>mind,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file the <hi>conſcience,</hi> ſo that he is a <hi>Rebel</hi> in all the height and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Being, and knowing no <hi>Body</hi> to defile him, as an <hi>Unclean Spirit,</hi> he diſhonours his nature, and againſt the <hi>God of Spirits</hi> does immediately make war. So then when our hearts are alike ſtain'd, when our <hi>Filthineſs</hi> becomes ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, we then bear his Image in the true Character. Now what can be greater diſgrace to our Natures than this is? For the higheſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection we can ever arrive to is to be <hi>like God;</hi> and that is to reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him in <hi>Holineſs,</hi> which chiefly conſiſts in the <hi>purity of our minds;</hi> On the other ſide the greateſt <hi>Fall</hi> we can be ever condemn'd to, is to be <hi>like Satan,</hi> and that is to reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him in <hi>Uncleanneſs,</hi> which chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:41913:47"/>conſiſts in the <hi>foulneſs</hi> of our <hi>Souls;</hi> whence theſe Souls of ours muſt needs contract a great guilt, when bad thoughts do defile them; wherein we carry the very picture of the Father, and bear his ſtamp in the crime.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As they are the <hi>work,</hi> ſo they are the full <hi>delight</hi> of the Inward man. Here the Soul <hi>centers</hi> within it ſelf, and uncontrollably embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces its own actings; and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretneſs of thoſe ſtains renders them difficult to be cleanſed; whereas theſe <hi>fleſhly motions</hi> cannot breed any fulneſs of pleaſure; and their pollutions being evident, do often check the committer with thoſe Three reſtraints to a Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Being, which are <hi>Law, Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and <hi>Fame.</hi> And therefore changes are many times wrought in the greateſt Sinners; but when Sin once retires to <hi>Inviſible Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:41913:47"/>it is ſeldom deſtroy'd, becauſe neither Law nor Fame have here place, and Conſcience is too weak to overcome. Upon this account the labour of cleanſing is here ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and the Soul muſt be brought to encounter it ſelf in all the <hi>ſubtilty of a reforming,</hi> that we may preſent to our God in Pure Fleſh a mortified Spirit.</p>
            <p>Now ſhould Uncleanneſs be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly cheriſhed, what-ever the outward acts of ſanctity be, they are to be reckoned no better than <hi>Pilate</hi>'s purifying before the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, when he waſht his hands, but ſuffered the guilt of the moſt innocent <hi>Blood</hi> to paſs uncleanſed. Yet how many are there that reſt in a Shape and Outſide of Piety! a Privilege (if they will call it one) which the <hi>Old Serpent</hi> can challenge; who in the midſt of his Curſe does yet <hi>gild</hi> his <hi>Spots</hi> with
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41913:48"/>
               <hi>fair Light,</hi> and in a <hi>form</hi> of <hi>Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> lays his <hi>Sting.</hi> But a <hi>Bodily purging</hi> (take it at the beſt) is only the <hi>Preface</hi> to a new Life: an intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductory part to true Holineſs: It is a Dedication of the <hi>Court</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Offering upon the <hi>Altar;</hi> and 'tis the Altar you know ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the Gift; ſo 'tis the Heart that qualifies the performance. If we go no higher than <hi>bare Fleſh,</hi> we are but like the <hi>Bullocks</hi> that were <hi>cleanſed;</hi> but if beſides that Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying we are ſpiritually Holy, we become like the <hi>Prieſt</hi> that <hi>ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to attain ſuch a ſtate as that is, a watchful jealouſie is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite over our Souls: and here, as we muſt doubtfully <hi>ſuſpect,</hi> ſo we ought immediately to <hi>ſuppreſs</hi> any ſpringing Temptation. It is eaſie to caſt out the Adverſary while he is weak; ſuch are all
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:41913:48"/>Filthy Thoughts in their <hi>Infancy;</hi> but let them once ſpread and grow in the mind, then it is difficult for any one to check and ſubdue them. Who knows not what eaſineſs there is in quenching a <hi>ſpark,</hi> or turning as one pleaſes a <hi>little cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent?</hi> But if the Spark gets fewel to feed on, and enlarges it ſelf into a great Flame, how often does it mock mens labour and pains to hinder the miſchief of its progreſs? So likewiſe a little cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, if it be ſupplyed from Floods, and allowed to ſwell with freſh ſtreams, how ungovernable is its courſe! After the ſame manner do <hi>Spiritual Luſtings</hi> prove furious and wild, when they get their fewel and ſupply from the will and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections flowing in. It is very needful then for thee to guard thy <hi>Heart,</hi> which is ſo apt to breed ſin, and ſo ready to ſtrengthen an
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:41913:49"/>evil purpoſe. But for the better ſecuring of it, oh labour ſtedfaſtly to apprehend thy God, not only as the accurate <hi>Beholder,</hi> but as the ſevere <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Puniſher</hi> of the Inner man. Indeed God does not exerciſe ſuch a Viſible Judgment upon any <hi>ſpiritual filthineſs</hi> in this World, becauſe He is mainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd here <hi>(as a Governour)</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the miſchiefs of <hi>outward acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> for the better defence of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Fellowſhip; but when all worldly Societies ſhall ceaſe, and every one be ſummoned to his Tribunal, He will then proceed <hi>as a Lawgiver,</hi> demanding a ſtrict ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count according to the full extent and compaſs of his Laws; and ſo theſe <hi>Spiritual Sins</hi> will be viſibly puniſhed, in that they are ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident breaches of his Spiritual Commands. It is my duty then chiefly to prepare for that Day;
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:41913:49"/>nor am I ſo much to examin the manner of this Government in this life, as how He will deal with me in another: Since that is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſtate, wherein I ſhall be ever fixt and determined, and wherein his Juſtice (that ſummons me) will be clearly revealed. Thus ſhould every one employ his Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and whoever buſies himſelf in them, he will find this to be the fruit and ſucceſs of them, that he will thereby get armour of defence within, and diſcourage the <hi>Tempter</hi> from aſſaulting.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the <hi>Duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Third Particular I am to handle is</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Manner of performing the Duty enjoyn'd us; namely a <hi>Perfecting of Holineſs in Gods Fear:</hi> where we may note Two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Degree or Meaſure we ſhould contend after, namely <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:41913:50"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Inward Principle that ought to quicken us, a <hi>Godly Fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The former ſhows we need a continual Progreſs in a Religious courſe; the latter ſhows we need a faithful direction to a right ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the <hi>Degree</hi> or <hi>Meaſure</hi> we ſhould contend after, this imports no leſs than a ſummoning of all the Powers of the Soul, and the ſetting of a Task to our outward members, that both in Mind and Body we may render to our God an unſpotted Sacrifice. Such an Offering (as this is) is not in an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> to be performed; nor does God ſo ſit any Saint, as that his Initials ſhould be full. His <hi>Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of a Sinner may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat <hi>in one act,</hi> when he gives him a <hi>Legal diſcharge;</hi> but his <hi>Sanctifying</hi> of us is not thus <hi>perfected;</hi> becauſe it is ſuch a work of his Spirit in us,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:41913:50"/>that <hi>gradually</hi> proceeds to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling of Sin, and takes in our <hi>Endeavours</hi> to <hi>grow up</hi> and <hi>encreaſe</hi> in holy duties. There is firſt an <hi>Infancy</hi> in the new nature, where (all the parts being form'd) <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi> is written as a <hi>Character to be kept,</hi> but not its <hi>Weakneſs:</hi> for a farther advancement is ſtill look'd for; whence the ſtrength of Men and perfectneſs of Stature is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Truly how can we imagine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings ſhould ſuffice, or that we ſafely can reſt in them, when the remainders of concupiſcence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the temptations without to which we are ſubject, the proper fruits and effects of a Faith juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, laſtly, the neceſſity of imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our Divine Pattetn, do all call for labour, ſtrife and diligence in our Chriſtian race, that we fall not ſhort of Heaven by but a little
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:41913:51"/>entring the way thither? <hi>Naaman</hi>'s waſhing in <hi>Jordan ſeven times,</hi> as it repreſented to him the Greatneſs of his Leproſie, ſo it repreſents to us thoſe <hi>repeated acts</hi> God expects from us of a naked ſearch into our ways, and that accompanied with a frequent purging of all the filth we contracted. Here is an evidence of Gods <hi>adopting</hi> us that we do <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>finiſh and bring to end the work of Holineſs:</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we are as unſafe in our <hi>clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> as thoſe <hi>Swine</hi> were which the Devil hurried into the <hi>Sea,</hi> making their firſt <hi>cleanneſs</hi> and their laſt deſtruction to go together.</p>
            <p>But we muſt obſerve in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Principle</hi> that ought to quicken us, <hi>a Godly Fear;</hi> and this is the Point I ſhall conclude with.</p>
            <p>But ſome may ask why is <hi>Fear</hi> brought in when Gods <hi>Promiſes</hi> are
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:41913:51"/>the motive? Is not <hi>Love</hi> the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral conſequent of ſuch offers, and a Principle too of it ſelf more binding?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, <hi>Love</hi> is not the ſole conſequent, but <hi>Fear</hi> alſo, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thoſe conditions upon which the Promiſes hang; and this Fear of the Two is more binding; as urging upon us a ſenſe of danger, and thereby quickning us unto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; whereas Love without is faint, and altogether languiſhes in its working.</p>
            <p>Now this Principle of <hi>Godly Fear</hi> excludes utterly the Heathens way of purifying, as a <hi>Rite</hi> in its uſing <hi>unclean:</hi> For ſo every thing becomes to an Unbeliever: It excludes like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thoſe ſeeming religious acts of Pretending Chriſtians, who in the good things they do, have either a <hi>dread</hi> of <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> or the <hi>vanity</hi> of <hi>Opinion</hi> for their Object.
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:41913:52"/>The one conſiſts not with this in my Text, which purely terminates in God alone, and the other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys all the notion of a true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, when it ſets up an Idol of Applauſe.</p>
            <p>Yet thus do Hypocrites boaſt of Holineſs; to ſome parts of which perhaps Legal Terrors, or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Men may conſtrain them; nothing is natural in their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but forc'd; and the <hi>ſpring</hi> of their <hi>motion</hi> is without them; ſo that they are rather to be counted <hi>artificial Engines</hi> (produced to caſt forth water upon an <hi>open burning</hi>) than <hi>Chriſtians</hi> that are free and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive at all <hi>times</hi> to extinguiſh the Flame. But if ſuch as theſe be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, how much more the looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophane! who cannot be thought to have a touch of this Paſſion when they defy God and his Laws. Did a <hi>right fear</hi> once
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:41913:52"/>rule and ſway the Conſcience, it were neither poſſible for vice to be barefac'd, nor for Hypocriſie to be diſguiſed: The awe of a God would <hi>ſhame</hi> the one, and <hi>ſtrip</hi> the other of its <hi>Covering.</hi> But behold! the maſque, the diſguiſe is not ſo much the danger of this Age; we are fallen from <hi>ſhows</hi> to a <hi>contempt</hi> of Chriſtianity, from <hi>colours</hi> to <hi>open war:</hi> our <hi>paint</hi> is turn'd to <hi>rottenneſs;</hi> and the <hi>perfume</hi> of our Profeſſion is become like the <hi>air of ſnuffs,</hi> nay the noiſome <hi>ſmell</hi> of corrupted Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, that can <hi>kill</hi> at a <hi>diſtance,</hi> and by their power of Execution ſadly manifeſt Death has not deſtroy'd them. O the extremes of Sin! whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the triumph &amp; glory of our Religion departed! Is it not now a matter of boaſting to <hi>kick</hi> at <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> while the <hi>head</hi> at the ſame time <hi>knocks</hi> the <hi>Earth,</hi> and calls for the opening of a <hi>Grave?</hi> Is it not the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:41913:53"/>triumph of <hi>wit</hi> to ſport at a <hi>Luſt,</hi> when it reproaches the Committer in the act, and tells him farther by its <hi>ſting</hi> that his own <hi>ſcoffs</hi> are <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd?</hi> But what is it we truſt to in this our offending? God we know is above, has a hand of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to ſtrike, nor can any promiſe tye it up, when once forfeited by our tranſgreſſions. All our ſhift for ſinning is to hinder Conſcience from interpoſing, by cutting off all ſeriouſneſs of thought, and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately throwing our ſelves into a <hi>Gulf</hi> of pleaſure. In the mean time, while we are ſunk in ways of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, Judgment is ripening over us; clouds gather about us thicker and blacker, and the lightning of Gods wrath is fitted and prepared; nor can we eſcape the force of it, except we remove the Seeds of our ruine by a ſpeedy and univerſal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:41913:53"/>
            <p>The <hi>Spartans</hi> we read were great <hi>Worſhippers</hi> of the <hi>Paſsions;</hi> and therefore had <hi>Temples</hi> erected to them; but <hi>Fear</hi> was the <hi>Goddeſs</hi> they chiefly <hi>worſhipped</hi> in regard of its uſe and influence to preſerve States. Certainly though they er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in thus dedicating their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, yet they did not erre in their notion of the advantage of <hi>Fear:</hi> but had a <hi>godly one</hi> fully poſſeſſed them, they would much more have concluded the ſafety of a Nation to depend on it; as being the ſureſt Bond of Law, and the only preventer of Gods Plagues. I need not endeavour to prove ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe; for where ſuch a <hi>Fear</hi> has due place, it will in the <hi>cloſeſt ſecreſie</hi> oblige men to <hi>obey,</hi> and engage God <hi>openly</hi> to <hi>defend</hi> them. But whether outward proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity be always the fruit, I ſhall not enquire: I am ſure the ſucceſs
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:41913:54"/>is of the laſt day, and the ſentence of mercy waits onely upon thoſe that religiouſly <hi>fear</hi> to offend. To theſe no death can be ſudden nor untimely, which alone is the portion of impenitent ſinners; who fall often to the earth with their <hi>Youth</hi> and with their <hi>Sins</hi> too as <hi>full blown:</hi> and being caſt down by a Judgment, are not allowed a ſpace to recover them. Why then will we abuſe the promiſes that are offer'd us? There is a <hi>Golden thread</hi> of them let down from Heaven, but tyed to a <hi>Sword</hi> with the <hi>point</hi> over us; and while we are rioting and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulging the Fleſh, the thread is ready to break, and the Sword to fall on us.</p>
            <p>Pardon the harſhneſs of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing theſe things; for ſoft words are not for Miniſters to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver: It is your conſcience we are
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:41913:54"/>bound to ſtrike, whereas your eyes are enough enlightned. And the Corruption of mens natures re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires this Method, that <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Threatnings</hi> ſhould be joyn'd, to chaſtiſe and temper our hopes, and ſettle upon our ſpirits a right frame. Otherwiſe we ſhould bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſume, and learn no <hi>Holineſs in Gods Fear,</hi> but that Good and Evil poſſeſſing our thoughts, help to quicken us in our Obedience.</p>
            <p>So then I beſeech you contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate Divine Love, as withal fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to the refuſer: joyn the <hi>Father</hi> with the <hi>Judge,</hi> and the <hi>Adoption</hi> he offers with his <hi>Severity</hi> in <hi>condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:</hi> farther conſider how the <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of <hi>Humane Nature</hi> lies in the <hi>pureneſs of its faculties,</hi> as a <hi>Reward</hi> follows their <hi>Exerciſe:</hi> Firſt you are advanced by it to be like God, next in that likeneſs to enjoy him: Laſt of all, ſearch out every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:41913:55"/>to preſs you to Holineſs, which if you enter upon and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in, the ſame God (who was Gracious in making, and is Faithful in performing what He has promiſed) will enſtate you in the Inheritance of Sons, and add Eternity for its Crown.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="discourse">
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:41913:55"/>
            <head>The Third Diſcourſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>St. John 6.68.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Then Simon Peter anſwered him, Lord to whom ſhall we goe? Thou haſt the words of Eternal Life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IF you examin the ſcope of theſe words, they are a full and paſſionate reply to that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion Chriſt made in the verſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going, where He tries the Faith of his Apoſtles, whether they would conſtantly adhere to his Laws, or with the reſt of the Multitude for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him? For we read in this Chapter how that great Crowd of people which followed him, began now to ſhrink and fall off, becauſe his <hi>Doctrine</hi> was (like his <hi>Perſon</hi>)
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:41913:56"/>no wayes ſuited to a carnal Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion. And the colour they had for this their <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> was ſome <hi>ſuppoſed abſurdity</hi> of what he taught; as when He ſtyl'd himſelf <hi>the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Bread which came down from Heaven,
<note place="margin">verſ. 51.</note> and whoever eat of that Bread ſhould live for ever:</hi> So that we find upon an enquiry that a bare <hi>Metaphor</hi> was the quarrel, and a <hi>Figure of Speech</hi> the foundation of the Controverſie.</p>
            <p>But waving the ſubject matter of their Diſpute (which is at large deſcribed in the Chapter) it will not be impertinent to obſerve the ſtrange levity and ingratitude of the Vulgar, who being the worſt judges of a diſcourſe, will yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſit upon it; and if it once croſſes their fancy, they are ready to throw off the Authority of their Lord; ay and ſuch an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that was before highly
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:41913:56"/>commended to them in all the Wonders of Mercy. Hence it is ſaid (<hi>v.</hi> 66.) <hi>That many of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples went back, and walked no more with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon ſo general a <hi>revolt</hi> He ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears at that accident unconcern'd: whatever pitty He had for their perſons, yet He leavs them to be puniſhed by that <hi>flight</hi> they had made; but as for the <hi>Twelve</hi> (whom He had particularly choſen for his Attendants) theſe He deals with as a Friend, ſounds their Loyalty, and by his very ſeeming to doubt of it, ſhows all the Tenderneſs of a Saviour. <hi>Then ſaid He to the Twelve, Will ye alſo go away? Then Simon Peter anſwered him, Lord, to whom ſhall we go? Thou haſt the words of Eternal Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Anſwer of <hi>St. Peters</hi> we may conſider Two Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Senſe of all the Apoſtles
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:41913:57"/>delivered by one of them, which was plainly this, That they ought not to ſeek another Maſter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Reaſon of their Choice drawn from the ſingular excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his <hi>Teaching, Thou haſt the words of Eternal Life.</hi>—</p>
            <p>I begin with their General Senſe, <hi>Lord to whom ſhall we go?</hi> which kind of ſpeech does imply, that ſhould they offer to leave Chriſt, yet a Maſter was needful to be their Guide in Religion. For ſuch is mans weakneſs and poverty by nature, that he requires ſomewhat without him to reſt on for Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: but it here farther fignifies, that they were already fixt upon a Teacher, and could find out nothing comparable to him they heard. This is the ſcope and meaning of the Queſtion.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>Matter</hi> thus declared and from the <hi>Occaſion</hi> of doing it
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:41913:57"/>we may note Two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Nobleneneſs of a right Faith when once ſeated in the Soul.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Authority of Truth not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Oppoſition of the World.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Nobleneſs of a right Faith,</hi> &amp;c.— And it is this, That it ſets upon Difficulties and conquers them: Let the times of Profeſſion be bad and reproachful too for thoſe numbers that backſlide, yet he that is well grounded in his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, has his thoughts higher plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. He is above the Poor Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time, and beyond the Contagion of an Example. Now the rules that govern moſt men in their courſe are Private Intereſt and Publick Opinion; ſo that like <hi>Puppits</hi> they move, and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of their acting is without them; but he that is led by nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:41913:58"/>of theſe, but makes <hi>Religion</hi> his <hi>Intereſt,</hi> and obedience to it his <hi>Fame,</hi> he may be call'd a Believer indeed: for he expreſſes the Man and the Chriſtian together. Others are but <hi>Reeds</hi> in their Station, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with every <hi>wind,</hi> and mark'd for their <hi>barrenneſs</hi> while they ſtand: but he is a <hi>Tree</hi> ſet by the <hi>Rivers of water,</hi> that has <hi>depth</hi> of root and <hi>fruitfulneſs</hi> to crown it. Yet the conſtancy he has is not any ſtiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mind, that proceeds from the prejudice of Education; for that is no better than the <hi>ſtiffneſs of earth,</hi> which is ſenſeleſs in that condition; but it is a vigorous judgment ſways him to the act, and confirms his faculties in work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>I grant it very difficult at firſt to <hi>believe,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Enmity of Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Sophiſtry of Reaſon,</hi> which is <hi>Fleſh</hi> ſet out in <hi>another fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure;</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:41913:58"/>but where <hi>Faith</hi> gets an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, there fleſh is ſubdued and reaſon anſwer'd, &amp; the heart comes prepared to embrace Chriſtianity in its hardeſt terms. For this is a Principle that humbles and lays us low, and diſcovers our weakneſs to our ſelves: It forces us to confeſs that God has <hi>depths</hi> of his own we cannot fathom; and ſince we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low our aſſent to <hi>Myſteries</hi> in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> no leſs ought we to do ſo to <hi>Myſteries</hi> in <hi>Religion,</hi> though not to be explain'd by our narrow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. This was the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles caſe, who learnt to ſubmit to the Doctrine that was preach'd, and deriv'd from that ſubmiſſion a courage to adhere. Let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider next</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Authority of Truth notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Oppoſition of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God never left himſelf without witneſs in the midſt of the greateſt
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:41913:59"/>Apoſtacies. He had <hi>Noah</hi> to be his Champion in the <hi>Old World, Elijah</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and Apoſtles in the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> that kept up Religion from periſhing. <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Light</hi> have this property common to them both, that as they are apt to be clouded, ſo they have vertue to break through thoſe Miſts that interpoſe. There is a natural Soveraignty in them both, and they ſeem to be born to an Univerſal Inheritance: though they may be as Strangers and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iles in ſome lands, yet in others they take the Poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>We all know the force of a <hi>good title,</hi> how it prevails. If a <hi>Prince</hi> of undoubted right be caſt off by the vile treachery of his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, yet his <hi>Title</hi> will ſtill rule; powerfully poſſeſſing the peoples hearts, and as ſtrongly <hi>warring</hi> in the <hi>conſcience</hi> of an <hi>Uſurper.</hi> The
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:41913:59"/>like command has the Cauſe of <hi>Truth</hi> amongſt Men, and a ſurer too; for a People may be ſcourg'd by a total loſs of their Prince; but Gods Faithfulneſs is ingag'd to maintain the Dominion of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He that created and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed all things by the <hi>word of his power,</hi> has ſpoken this, that Truth ſhall for ever endure; and in order to accompliſh what He has ſpoken, he employs his <hi>Spirit</hi> to work; gives us natures inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive and reflecting, whereby we are ſtirred up to the duties of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; ſo that as long as the <hi>Spirit</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bides (which is <hi>eternal</hi>) as long as <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> laſt (which are <hi>eſſential</hi> to our <hi>frame</hi>) the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of Religion muſt for ever remain. Whether it be of the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Gods <hi>Church</hi> to be always viſible, I ſhall not diſcuſs; but the foundation upon which it is built,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:41913:60"/>can certainly never fail, ſince He is God that is laid there. <hi>For other Foundation can no man lay, than that is laid, which is Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Should we now on the other ſide conſider the growth of <hi>Error,</hi> and the fair ſhow it makes in the world, we cannot conclude hence that it has ſtrength to continue. For ſtrength preſuppoſes a real exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence in the Subject; whereas <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror</hi> is of it ſelf a <hi>meer nothing,</hi> and ows to <hi>Ignorance</hi> that it appears. It is a <hi>Ghoſt</hi> that walks in the <hi>dark,</hi> whoſe <hi>body</hi> is fram'd by our <hi>fancies,</hi> and when <hi>day</hi> comes, it <hi>vaniſhes</hi> with them. But to <hi>Truth</hi> a <hi>being</hi> pertains, and it conſtantly ſtrives to open its way into <hi>Light,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal that Being to others, which when effected, it gloriouſly ſpreads, and enlarges its <hi>Empire</hi> with that diſcovery.</p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:41913:60"/>
            <p>Before I paſs to the ſecond Head of my Diſcourſe, I ſhall briefly diſpatch one Quere, which is this: Why <hi>Simon Peter</hi> (that ſingly ſpoke here) ſhould ſo readily proclaim his own Faith, and undertake like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for the Faith of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> though a <hi>Judas</hi> was of their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            <p>Now the reaſon of this I can only reſolve into thoſe Two Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherein he excell'd <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Charity.</hi> The one made him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in a publick <hi>Confeſsion</hi> of <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> the other in a <hi>Defence</hi> of his <hi>Brethren.</hi> Zeal is a fire that will be ſure to get uppermoſt; whence our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> being heated with it, comes out firſt for his <hi>Lord;</hi> but then leſt the ambition of that act ſhould urge him to purſue his own Glory, he religiouſly ſuppreſſes it by his Charity to others. It is the nature of Charity to be kind, and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:41913:61"/>free from envy; not to ſeek her own but anothers praiſe: It treats all perſons alike, except ſome vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible fruits do diſtinguiſh them; and brings a Garment along with it of an equal breadth to hide eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry right Profeſſor; in a word, it is a generous Vertue, enobling our works of piety, and making us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to the world.</p>
            <p>This was the temper of our bleſſed <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> whom many are prone enough to imitate for his <hi>Zeal;</hi> but if this latter Grace be wanting, they ought to ſuſpect the birth of that <hi>flame;</hi> ſince the true <hi>Goſpel-fire</hi> that comes down from <hi>Heaven</hi> has a comforting warmth in it that <hi>heals,</hi> and tends not to kill, but to <hi>ſave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come now to my Second Head, where we have</p>
            <p n="2">2. The reaſon of their choice drawn from the ſingular Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:41913:61"/>of Chriſts Teaching— <hi>Thou haſt the words of Eternal Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It might be expected that <hi>poor Fiſhermen</hi> (as theſe were) ſhould have had <hi>Souls</hi> as <hi>low</hi> as their <hi>Trade:</hi> that they ſhould be far from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, and farther yet from pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing a ſtate of eternity; whoſe great end and buſineſs before was but the <hi>ſmall gain</hi> of a <hi>draught;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knew they how to prize any greater wealth, than what a <hi>Lake</hi> or a <hi>Brook</hi> contains. But ſee how Religion exalts them; what high thoughts are now form'd, and what vaſt deſires are rais'd in them by the force of their Maſters Diſcipline; ſo that they begin to deſpiſe a preſent Good, and breath after nothing but a future Reward. Temporal Dominion was below their aim; for who can imagine they ſhould propound to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves an <hi>Earthly Monarchy,</hi> that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:41913:62"/>ſtuck only to Chriſt for an <hi>Inviſible Crown?</hi> Truly the manner of his <hi>appearance</hi> in this our Fleſh, and the nature of his <hi>Doctrine</hi> taught them no other: His appearance was ſo mean that it was but the <hi>form of a Servant</hi> which He aſſum'd; Agen, his Doctrine was ſo <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> that He challeng'd only a <hi>Kingdom di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct</hi> from the <hi>World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 17.36, Luke 9.2.</note> and ſent on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Diſciples upon that Errand to <hi>preach</hi> it.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Pretended Succeſſors</hi> of <hi>St. Peter</hi> (who here follows his Lord for his <hi>Heavenly Miniſtry</hi>) can arrogantly purſue a <hi>worldly claim;</hi> as if <hi>Earth</hi> were in their <hi>Charter</hi> as well as <hi>Heaven,</hi> and therefore they ought to take both by <hi>violence,</hi> pull down Kings and Princes, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance themſelves to an arbitrary Greatneſs. Whoſe <hi>Apoſtles</hi> I pray are they that would thus rule? or by what right of donation do the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:41913:62"/>Kingdoms of the world belong to them? For we do not read they were any of thoſe <hi>Gifts Chriſt gave unto men,</hi> but onely the <hi>Devils offer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 Mat. 8.</note> which He rejected. I am ſure ſuch as theſe are the Greateſt Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of our Lord. The putting of a <hi>Reed</hi> into his hand before he ſhould <hi>ſuffer,</hi> was but the <hi>mocking</hi> of his <hi>Power;</hi> but to put a <hi>Sword</hi> into his hand that is come to <hi>ſave</hi> us, is a flat denyal of his <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> and ſo they impiouſly number him with the <hi>Tranſgreſſors.</hi> I need not farther enlarge on this Subject, nor demonſtrate the wildneſs of their Tenet, which both our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Life, and manner of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, the Commands and Practiſe of the Apoſtles, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of primitive Martyrs, and in a word, the Profeſſion of the beſt Saints has condemn'd. But this by the way—It here lies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:41913:63"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:41913:63"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:41913:64"/>me to prove how Chriſts <hi>words</hi> are the <hi>proper words</hi> of <hi>Eternal Life;</hi> which may be eaſily made out from that Goſpel he has deliver'd to his Church; wherein we find him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A Miniſter,</hi> in that He has fully reveal'd it to the World.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>A Purchaſer,</hi> in that he has acquired a right to beſtow it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>A Worker,</hi> in that He has made the Doctrine of it effectual to Salvation.</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>A Miniſter, in that he has fully reveal'd it to the World,</hi> as He did alſo the Doctrine of <hi>Eternal Death,</hi> which I before handled. And He has revealed <hi>this Life</hi> in a way of Authority and Sweetneſs proper to himſelf, at once forcing us to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the truth of that evidence, and raiſing our affections to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue it. He therefore delivered it in ſuch a Style that might power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:41913:64"/>engage us both ways: as when He did not onely expreſly mention the thing it ſelf, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deſcribed it by ſuch inviting Characters, as <hi>Joy, Glory, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven;</hi> nay, in a peculiar Emphaſis, <hi>the Kingdom</hi> where Life and Immortality are <hi>enthron'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now who is there but muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the blindneſs that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd the <hi>Gentile World,</hi> till this Great Prophet came to enlighten us? For we ſat in darkneſs, and in the very ſhadow of Death, which encompaſſed us round and beſet us, and took away from us any farther Proſpect; not to be open'd nor enlarg'd, till this Light came, which <hi>gave us Knowledg and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> What force ſoever there may be in <hi>Natural Religion</hi> (which ſome boaſt of) yet the great Maſters of thoſe Schools which taught it, were miſerably dimſighted as to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:41913:65"/>any future ſtate of Life and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, except wee'l ſay a walk in <hi>Elyſium</hi> for <hi>Wandring Souls,</hi> or a wretched <hi>Pilgrimage</hi> through <hi>ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Bodies,</hi> be a proper Condition to be deſired. Yet thus did the beſt of thoſe Writers dream, who apprehended well enough a God and his Worſhip; and though they might deliver fine notions of both, yet <hi>fancy</hi> came in to corrupt all with groſs devices and fooliſh mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in their Reward. Hence the morality even of their Chiefeſt was ſuited to their Principles; that is, They had the <hi>Shadow</hi> of a <hi>Good Life,</hi> as they had the <hi>Shadow of Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi> The greateſt height of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue they ever arriv'd to, was but to diſguiſe their Paſſions, and by ſtopping ſome foul effects of them to conſult a Fame of well-doing, whereas the ſeed and root of a corruption was ſtill cheriſhed, and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:41913:65"/>luſt ſecretly ruled in their hearts and lives, for want of a diſcovery which we Chriſtians enjoy about the eternal Wages of our deeds. Upon this account <hi>Tertullian</hi> and the reſt of the Ancients had ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ground to condemn their choiceſt <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> ſince the ſtudy of it was followed with no other fruit than this, That it ſerv'd for <hi>Paint</hi> to hide Vice, but prov'd no <hi>Antidote</hi> to expell it.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>Natural Reaſon</hi> did thus fail, muſt we alſo complain of any defect in thoſe <hi>Inſpirations</hi> which Gods own <hi>Prophets</hi> were aſſiſted with? No; for the words they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered were <hi>words of life:</hi> onely the <hi>Jews</hi> that heard them were in their nonage, bred up at firſt with <hi>milk and honey,</hi> and that <hi>Infant-food of a Carnal Promiſe:</hi> and therefore it was judg'd fit by Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to wean them by degrees
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:41913:66"/>from theſe outward things, and not allow them a <hi>Spiritual Diet</hi> of <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect happineſs,</hi> till they arrived at the ſtrength of a Maſculine Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. But the Prophets them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves had that ſtate revealed to them in all its clearneſs; only that <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> which their Hearers were under cauſi'd it to be diſpenc'd to them by a <hi>Figurative application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Chriſt came in the very fulneſs of time, when <hi>Life and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality</hi> were to be ſhown; and He anſwer'd that fulneſs by his own Teaching: ſo that all thoſe Prophets who went before him, ſerv'd but like the light of a <hi>Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-ſtar</hi> to uſher in the brightneſs of that diſcovery. Let us conſider him in the next place.</p>
            <p n="2">II. As a <hi>Purchaſer, in that He acquir'd a right to beſtow it.</hi> And this Title He has to ſuch a donation by that Price he laid down for his
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:41913:66"/>own People, when He bought them out of their old Thraldom, and cancell'd that forfeiture they had made of <hi>Life Eternal,</hi> by the merits of his Death, and the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Satisfaction of his Sufferings. His Goſpel is the Evidence of this his Purchaſe, wherein <hi>Eternal Life</hi> and our Lords <hi>Propriety</hi> is declard; whereby He is qualified not only to poſſeſs it <hi>in himſelf,</hi> but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre that Inheritance upon <hi>others.</hi> And therefore to him we muſt have recourſe in all our Devotions, and upon his <hi>Merits alone</hi> ground our addreſſes,
<note place="margin">Heb. 7.25.</note> 
               <hi>who is able to ſave to the uttermoſt them that come unto God by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> ſeem to have found out other Purchaſers, at leaſt many Sharers with him in that Prerogative; when dividing the Vertue of his Mediation, they fly to <hi>Saints and Angels</hi> by a <hi>ſolemn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation</hi>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:41913:67"/>of them to intercede. What is this elſe but an <hi>Idolatrous act,</hi> when the <hi>Creature</hi> is ſet up by them for a peculiar <hi>Object</hi> they muſt <hi>adore,</hi> and for a <hi>Meritorious Helper they ſhould truſt to?</hi> or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in do they differ from the old <hi>Heathens,</hi> who worſhipped their <hi>Demons</hi> or Inferiour Gods as <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Agents</hi> with the <hi>Supreme?</hi> If they upon that ſcore were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as <hi>Idolaters</hi> by the ancient maintainers of our Religion, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a like charge does moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly fall upon ſuch Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers that parcel out and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate <hi>Divine Glory;</hi> nay, the Charge is much heavier in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, becauſe the Heathens were ignorant of Gods will; but for Chriſtians this way to <hi>beg life,</hi> it is to libel Gods Word that ſpeaks o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; it is to exclude his Son from his own Office and Royalty,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:41913:67"/>in whoſe <hi>Name</hi> we are bid <hi>to pray,</hi> and by whom <hi>alone</hi> we have acceſs to our Heavenly Father; nay it is repugnant to the condition of thoſe <hi>Spirits</hi> above, who can neither hear every mans prayers throughout the world, nor look into the hearts of thoſe that call on them. Yet O ye bleſſed Saints and Angels (if ye can behold ſuch Worſhippers as theſe men) ſee with what wicked Plots and bloody hands they offer Incenſe: Can ye poſſibly accept their Prayers. No, none can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them but their own <hi>Martyrs.</hi> But all Worſhip (how innocent ſoever) is rejected in Heaven, where the God of it alone is not ſought to: therefore the right ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Life</hi> is from him, who can onely give <hi>Grace,</hi> and lift us up to his own <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. The third and laſt way we are to conſider him is, As a <hi>Worker,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:41913:68"/>in that he has made the Doctrine of Eternal Life effectual to Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this <hi>Word</hi> (He has commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd us to preach) is the great Inſtrument of the New-birth: It is a means to beget in us a <hi>true Faith,</hi> and being once ſtedfaſtly embraced, it gives us the firſt-fruits of Eternal Life, till we are fully inveſted in the Inheritance. What was heretofore the vertue of his <hi>Word</hi> at the creation of all things, when he ſpoke out a World, and call'd it forth into an actual Being, the ſame is the vertue of his written Word, whereby he calls Us to an Eternal one. For the <hi>All-quickning Spirit</hi> is mixt with it; whence it becoms fruitfully ſtrong and mighty to ſave thoſe that hear. What Rock is there ſo hard, or Ground ſo barren, that can reſiſt the influence of its power? How does it cut through a <hi>heart of ſtone,</hi> and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:41913:68"/>cultivate the <hi>De ſart</hi> of <hi>wild paſsions!</hi> How does it mould and faſhion us to become a people acceptable to the Lord! If natural inclination or carnal intereſt ſhould ſtand up to oppoſe it, theſe are but like <hi>Muddy Fortreſſes</hi> that are quickly batter'd and diſſolv'd; and a new frame is ſet up in the ſoul, that is pure and heavenly; which expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the Agent in the <hi>Divinity</hi> of his work, and ſhows the beauty of thoſe <hi>Promiſes</hi> he applies, in ſuch motions that bend wholly towards them. This Spirit of old (which worked by the Word) drew mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of men to Chriſtianity, beating down in them the ſtrong holds of ſin and Satan, fanctifying their natures, and ſo giving them a new reliſh of things; raiſing their love to a Chriſt crucified, and their deſires after a diſtant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; whence they would not ſo
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:41913:69"/>much as receive <hi>their good things here,</hi> in hopes of a <hi>richer treaſure hereafter.</hi> Truly even the Word it ſelf did much perſwade: but the <hi>Spirit</hi> came in with a <hi>Demonſtration;</hi> whereby they gave up their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſts, ſurrendred their darling luſts, and caſting out every thing that reſiſted, yielded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves abſolutely to his conduct.</p>
            <p>Theſe things conſidered, who can deny the <hi>fulneſs</hi> of his <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> that ſees Heaven and Hell in their diſtinct lights ſet before him, which heretofore were either <hi>quencht</hi> by <hi>Fables,</hi> or under <hi>Shadows conceal'd?</hi> Who can deny the <hi>right</hi> of his <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe,</hi> that beholds the merit of his Sufferings, for which his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature was lifted up, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in full power to ſit on the Throne and pronounce <hi>life</hi> to his followers? As little can we deny the Third way, namely the <hi>Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:41913:69"/>of his <hi>Doctrine</hi> to lead us thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if we either reflect upon it as the Power of God, or the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral tendency of it to work in us a ſpirit of Holineſs, and ſo fit us for Glory. Theſe things <hi>St. Peter</hi> had reſpect to when he ſo emphatical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tells his Maſter, <hi>Thou haſt the words of eternal life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Phraſe <hi>(Eternal Life)</hi> is a ſhort deſcription of the good mans future eſtate; nor is it otherwiſe ever mentioned in Scripture than as ſignifying the Saints Portion: ſo that for Chriſt to have <hi>words</hi> of that kind, is to have in ſtore for him a double Bleſſing: For when He ſpeaks <hi>life,</hi> he puts him into <hi>poſſeſsion</hi> of an <hi>Inheritance;</hi> when he ſpeaks an <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> he gives him a <hi>ſecurity</hi> of <hi>enjoying:</hi> whence he mercifully joyns them in his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of bliſs, as they are neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily joyn'd in the notion.</p>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:41913:70"/>
            <p>I ſhall not trouble my Reader with a farther Comment, nor run into a controverſie whether there be indeed ſuch an eſtate that we from Scripture are aſſur'd Chriſt ſpeaks of, it being no way pertinent to this Text I diſcuſs, nor I preſume to him that peruſes it; of whom I ought to ſuppoſe that Principles are believed, which neither imply in them a contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for <hi>Reaſon</hi> to cavil at, nor hazard for <hi>Wiſdom</hi> to fear.</p>
            <p>It remains I ſhould ſhow the force of the Argument why we ſhould ſtick cloſe to our Lord and Maſter from <hi>St. Peters</hi> ſuppoſition that the Doctrine of <hi>Eternal Life</hi> proceeds from him.</p>
            <p>It were much to be wiſh'd that the rules he lays down for our Courſe upon earth might bind fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers to him without ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal as that is; ſince they yield
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:41913:70"/>us a preſent pay in <hi>Honour, Eaſe,</hi> and <hi>Bleaſure,</hi> that do certainly wait upon vertuous actions: But if Fleſh be ſo ſtrong as to reject thoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives by reaſon of the narrowneſs of their limits, how can we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude an <hi>Eternity</hi> of all theſe, where it adds another Good, <hi>ſafety</hi> to perfect them? Behold! there is in that ſtate of Eternal Life a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat anſwer to thoſe two Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that govern us here, and make our life a torment to us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they be ſatisfied. For</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Gift is ſo vaſt that it ſwallows up Hope.</p>
            <p n="2">2. So durable that it removes Fear.</p>
            <p>Now in all <hi>Hope</hi> there is want, and <hi>deſire</hi> is nothing elſe but a <hi>cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving emptineſs</hi> in the <hi>Soul.</hi> That <hi>hungry Gueſt</hi> is often call'd to an <hi>Epicures Feaſt,</hi> and as often ſpoils it, turning his <hi>Plenty</hi> into <hi>Penance</hi> ſince
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:41913:71"/>it cannot fill. The like vanity of Imperfection cleaves to other worldly enjoyments, becauſe the eye of our mind (being too big for them) has an unquiet Appetite of looking farther. But it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble there ſhould be any place for that reſtleſs Paſſion where an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Good</hi> is injoyed: For this is an Object which tranſcends even our thoughts, ſurpaſſes our fancies that our deſires are founded on, and ſo delightfully keeps us within its <hi>Circle:</hi> All that we can imagine is there preſent, and therefore all we can <hi>hope for</hi> has in that preſence an <hi>end.</hi> Hence we come ſettled to thoſe Joys, and bring a ſpirit full and entire to feed on them: ſo that there is no colour for a depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to a leſſer Good, that leaves us ſtill diſſatisfied in our fruition. Such are all Temporal Objects we purſue: they naturally tempt us to
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:41913:71"/>fall off from that chaſe, becauſe they do not anſwer our expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I mean while another is in our view, that (being eternal) commands our deſires, fulfils our hopes, and cures the defect of both with the ſatisfying wideneſs of its compaſs.</p>
            <p>Next for <hi>Fear:</hi> this inſeparably attends us in life; and argues not onely <hi>want and emptineſs,</hi> but the <hi>miſery and pain</hi> of it. <hi>Hope</hi> may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict us for the abſence of a Good, but then it ſome way chears us for the likelihood of attaining it; but <hi>Fear</hi> is a paſſion that eats into our delights, and devours all our Contentments. Neither can we poſſibly be freed from it, while we reflect upon thoſe changes which the <hi>Stage</hi> of this World ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes us to; States and Kingdoms being ſhifted there like <hi>Scenes,</hi> and almoſt with the ſame <hi>quickneſs.</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:41913:72"/>But the Doctrine of <hi>Eternal Life</hi> (Chriſt promiſes) is a Soveraign remedy againſt all trouble; for it ſhows us a <hi>fixt point,</hi> an <hi>unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able inſtant;</hi> nor can we be afraid with that contemplation, no more than we are with the proſpect of Shores and Havens, that receive us ſafe from a Storm. How is the ſoul quieted to think that thoſe evils it ſuffers are paſſing away, and a ſettled reſt is prepared! With what peace does it apprehend a moments danger when a perfect Liberty is the recompence! This and much more does a <hi>bleſt Eternity</hi> import, and through that encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement is a Chriſtian arm'd to encounter any affliction.</p>
            <p>And ſo we read what a ſtoutneſs of ſpirit was rais'd in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Profeſſors, that preach'd up Chriſtianity and ventur'd all upon it. A bare Faith did not carry them
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:41913:72"/>to that act, but a Faith that was grounded upon the Heavenlineſs of the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> Courage of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> and Power of <hi>Miracles;</hi> ſtrong Promiſes that will infer as ſtrong Concluſions, except wee'l ſay Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth were combin'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a plot to abuſe, and the abuſe too muſt be this, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>cheating</hi> of an <hi>Idolatrous world</hi> into <hi>good living.</hi> Let the Scoffer count it madneſs to quit <hi>Senſe</hi> for a Good that is yet hid from him; I could tell him that even a <hi>Preſent Good</hi> is <hi>inviſible;</hi> for we want time to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern it for its <hi>ſhortneſs,</hi> we want a Subſtance to be diſcern'd for its <hi>emptineſs;</hi> whereas an <hi>eternal</hi> one is <hi>inviſible</hi> for its <hi>tranſcendent fulneſs.</hi> Thither does right Reaſon drive us, and a true principle of Self-love, it being our intereſt to ſeek a Treaſure that will not fail us.</p>
            <p>But ſhould we take the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:41913:73"/>ſtate to This Life, namely <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Death</hi> which is the Curſe he threatens to thoſe that deny him) here we are ty'd to our Maſters ſervice by a ſure chain, which the dread of Omnipotence puts on. Earthly Powers can awe their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and juſtly too, with what they are able outwardly to inflict; yet Death (being the utmoſt ſtroke of that Juſtice) ſeems indeed but a retreat from it. But the <hi>Grave</hi> (how free and quiet ſoever it be) is no Sanctuary to keep us from Gods hand: It diſſolves our <hi>Bodies,</hi> but not his <hi>Government;</hi> who watches every particle of our duſt, and locks it up ſafe for an after-ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; but the Soul He makes the the immediate ſubject of his Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal. Therefore the higheſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage may be well demanded of us, upon whom the higheſt Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty is ſhown.</p>
            <pb n="133" facs="tcp:41913:73"/>
            <p>I confeſs none come up from the dead to tell us this news: no, they cannot; for the Judges Sentence binds them to their ſeats, where their great part is ſuffering; and if they could, 'tis uſeleſs, no ways tending to ſettle our Faith, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirming our ſuſpicion that in Satans Errand ſome <hi>Ghoſt</hi> may be employed. If <hi>Scripture</hi> (which <hi>St. Peter</hi> calls a <hi>light that ſhineth in a dark place)</hi> be with all its evidence of Divine Witneſſes diſown'd, how can we believe a teſtimony from the <hi>Damn'd,</hi> that would be ſure to bring with them all their <hi>night</hi> to <hi>deceive?</hi> This then can be no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. The true one is form'd by our own corrupt hearts; and we are apt to queſtion the Evil-day, becauſe we would not be checkt nor controll'd in our fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. In the mean time we baffle that deſign by ſtarting ſuch a
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:41913:74"/>doubt; which unſettling the ſoul in its pleaſures, does thereby hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it from enjoying them. We labour to be <hi>Scepticks</hi> that we may offend, and after we are ſo, we find our ſelves pain'd with that Uncertainty. Oh let us be wiſe for our latter end, and chooſe to ſerve our God by a true Faith, ſince our endeavouring to ſhake it does but wake Conſcience to torture us.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I have handled the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument St. Peter</hi> lays down for fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his <hi>Lord,</hi> and by the way toucht upon the Sinners <hi>Judgment:</hi> I have ſhown the <hi>nobleneſs</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> the <hi>authority</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent manner</hi> of revealing it by Chriſt above all thoſe diſcoveries that were made: The natural reſult from all is this, that we would ſeriouſly inquire whether we can better our life under another ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and if that be not poſſible,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:41913:74"/>then immediately liſt our ſelves his Diſciples in all the watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Devotion.</p>
            <p>As to the matter of <hi>Inquiry,</hi> it becomes us as men not to take any Maſter upon truſt, or the cuſtome of others: Credulity is proper to Children that are weak and want ſinews; but the ſtrength of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom conſiſts in this, <hi>to prove all things,</hi> and not be eaſily govern'd in our actings. Yet this childiſh weakneſs are moſt men ſubject to in their main end, when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh their own Faculties that would lead them to Chriſtianity; and ſuffer themſelves to be led by a Cuſtomary Diſcipline that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys it. What that teaching is, and how far it extends, every one knows: The mind is not taught here, but the <hi>brutiſh part</hi> and ſome <hi>tranſient reward</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to encourag it: Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:41913:75"/>I call it with reſpect to thoſe two <hi>Maſters</hi> that rule over us, <hi>Fleſh</hi> and the <hi>World,</hi> which pretend to nothing higher in their offers of Good; for all the colour they have to invite us is only the gratifying of our ſenſes for a few moments; onely <hi>Satan</hi> makes bold to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit our Lord, and wears his ſhape in a <hi>full promiſe,</hi> that ſo his hook may the better faſten and catch our appetite when he tempts us. He has therefore in readineſs for his followers <hi>words of Eternal Life</hi> (as he had for <hi>Eve</hi>) but thoſe very words prove fatal; for with the ſame breath he kills the Sholar that hears him. What other effect can be look'd for from a <hi>Serpent condemn'd?</hi> who delights in the ſpreading of his plague, and knows no other liberty from torment, than that pleaſure he takes in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging his <hi>Hell.</hi> To this end he
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:41913:75"/>continues down the poyſon of that Doctrine <hi>(Eat and live, ſin and be happy)</hi> in the mouths of his <hi>Falſe-Prophets;</hi> who are very buſie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile Faith with an Evil Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and would fain compound up a <hi>Religion of Fleſh;</hi> which are arts indeed to draw many after them in regard they <hi>bribe</hi> their Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality: But let us ſee the iſſue of all this, and what fruit there is in obeying ſuch Doctrines, when the Good (there promiſed) is <hi>blown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> with our <hi>breath,</hi> and inſtead of light we find darkneſs.</p>
            <p>On the contrary under Chriſts rule we have an <hi>Eternal Life</hi> ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to us in all certainty; and the condition He requires of us is an excellent part of that <hi>Life,</hi> ſince it gives us a proper <hi>Eye</hi> to enjoy it: The condition I mean is Purity of Heart, a Grace that doubly profits the Soul, firſt in <hi>refining</hi> our natures,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:41913:76"/>next in <hi>ſtrengthening</hi> us to <hi>ſee</hi> Glory. Who would not endeavour to be thus qualified for Heaven? Can any corruption move us to forfeit Security? and can there be greater ſecurity than the Good here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed? Mans <hi>Knowledge</hi> you will grant is much <hi>exalted</hi> in <hi>foreſeeing</hi> future things, but his <hi>Reaſon</hi> is more <hi>advanc'd</hi> in <hi>purſuing</hi> them. And whither would we go from our Lord? Other Offerers of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs do betray us; He onely can ſave. To him Nature has ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted us as being made; Gratitude as being redeem'd; Intereſt as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting a reward: ſo that to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him our hearts is to joyn Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege and folly together, when we rob God and impoveriſh our ſelves.</p>
            <p>We are all covetous of <hi>Life,</hi> and of Life too in its beſt eſtate. For though ſin has corrupted mens
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:41913:76"/>choice of the <hi>way,</hi> yet it has not blaſted their deſires of the end. But our Lord has farther provided thoſe deſires ſhould not be fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if we follow his rule, and ſtrictly adhere to his Commands in <hi>mortifying</hi> our <hi>affections and luſts,</hi> and as it were <hi>ſpirituallizing</hi> the <hi>whole man</hi> to be thereby fitted for his Kingdom. It is from us he expects this work ſhould be performed, and not from <hi>age:</hi> Age may indeed prove the <hi>mortifier</hi> of a <hi>Luſt,</hi> but withall it <hi>kills</hi> the <hi>ſervice.</hi> Little is the glory of overcoming the <hi>Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> when he does not aſſault us; but to break fleſhly motions in all their ſtrength this is a true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. Neither ſhould it be thought ſtrange for any Diſciple to deny thus <hi>ſelf</hi> in Chriſtianity; for <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> being the object of that work will eaſily deſtroy the Miracle of doing it. How can any of us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:41913:77"/>the happineſs above, and yet not be willing to forſake his proper ſins, ſins (how colour'd ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever) yet in the midſt of their <hi>Var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> deform'd! Where is true beauty but that of <hi>Life,</hi> which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the <hi>Counterfeit</hi> we admire? where is true wealth but that of <hi>Immortality,</hi> which only in the <hi>Glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> we eſteem! ſince then ſuch a fair and ſubſtantial Treaſure is there offer'd us, we ought like wiſe-men to determine our choice; and forſaking the vanities of other objects, become fixt and ſettled in our endeavours, that we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and compaſs that Good which yields ſo bright, ſo weighty, ſo glorious a recompence to the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuer.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="discourse">
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:41913:77"/>
            <head>The Fourth Diſcourſe.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 8.34.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Who is he that condemneth? It is Chriſt that died, yea rather that is riſen again.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe <hi>Juſtification</hi> of a Sinner, and the way God has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to ſave men by, is ſo miſtaken in the world, that no Point has begot more diſputes, nor is there any Theme wherein Scripture has more ſuffer'd. Yet this <hi>quarrel</hi> amongſt men cannot be charg'd upon any want of evidence in this particular; but either an <hi>humour of pride</hi> to contradict, or the <hi>intereſt of a Party</hi> to purſue, or the <hi>prejudice of Opinion</hi> to defend, have
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:41913:78"/>been the main cauſe of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. Would we come with a ſincere mind to the reading of the Word, eſpecially the Writings of this <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> we ſhould find the difficulty of that <hi>Truth</hi> clear'd, and the glorious effects of <hi>Chriſts Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatorſhip</hi> laid open, upon which our <hi>Juſtifying</hi> does depend.</p>
            <p>Now for the better handling this Text (which I have here cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to diſcuſs) I ſhall a little ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the verſe before it, by reaſon of their neceſſary connexion toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In which verſe we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Triumphant Challenge he makes, ſummoning any Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to appear in <hi>Court</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Who will charge or accuſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Ground of his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence how little that <hi>Accuſation</hi> would avail, becauſe of the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Judge that <hi>acquits</hi> the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:41913:78"/>offendor.—<hi>It is God that juſtifies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The limitation of the <hi>Charge</hi> in reſpect of the party againſt whom it is drawn, and the limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the act of <hi>Juſtifying Grace</hi> in reſpect of the party to whom it belongs—<hi>Who will lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? It is God that juſtifies,</hi> that is thoſe <hi>Elect:</hi> where by Gods <hi>Elect</hi> he means the ſame that are ſpoken of in the firſt verſe of the Chapter, namely ſuch as <hi>are in Chriſt Jeſus, that walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit:</hi> that is, who perform all the conditions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the <hi>New Covenant:</hi> For theſe alone are the choſen of God, whom He has decreed to reward with Eternal Life.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the grace of <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> does neceſſarily ſuppoſe a work of <hi>Satisfaction</hi> (ſince the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God could have no place for <hi>juſtifying</hi> a ſinner, were not the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:41913:79"/>way firſt made by <hi>attoning</hi> his <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi>) he therefore proceeds in my Text to clear that point, and ſhow whence <hi>Pardoning Mercy</hi> ſprings, namely from Chriſts undertaking our Cauſe, and reconciling us to his Father by the vertue of his Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſhip.
<note place="margin">Acts 4.11, 12.</note> He indeed is the <hi>Stone</hi> upon which all our ſalvation is built, ſo that without him there neither is nor can be given either Pardon of ſin here, or Glory hereafter. Hence the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> with regard to his <hi>ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> does further urge, and more ſtrongly confirm what he laid down in the former verſe, <hi>Who is he that condemneth? it is Chriſt that died, yea rather that is riſen again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words contain in them a True Believers <hi>full diſcharge;</hi> and the <hi>Reaſon</hi> or Ground of it. The fulneſs of the diſcharge is held forth in that Queſtion, <hi>Who is he that condemneth?</hi> The reaſon of it
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:41913:79"/>is expreſt in that double work of our Redeemer, but one of them more dignified than the other. <hi>It is Chriſt that died; yea, rather is riſen again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſenſe of the whole may be reſolv'd into theſe Three Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there is a Proper and Peculiar Vertue to be aſcribed to Chriſts <hi>Death</hi> in the act of redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That there are Proper and Peculiar Advantages in Chriſts <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> above that Death.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Chriſts <hi>Death</hi> in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, but more eminently his <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> has procur'd the Saints free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from Condemnation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That there is a Proper and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Vertue to be aſcribed to Chriſts Death in the act of Redeeming us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of it I ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſome Truths.</p>
            <pb n="146" facs="tcp:41913:80"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I take for granted what Scripture ſo clearly reveals, that the breach of a <hi>Poſitive Law</hi> (which was given to <hi>Adam</hi> in <hi>Paradiſe</hi>) did not onely involve him but his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity too in the Curſe there threatned; ſo that the propagation of <hi>Mankind</hi> from him was but the propagation of <hi>perſons condemn'd;</hi> all of us being lyable thereby to <hi>Death Temporal and Eternal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> though God conſidered in his <hi>Abſolute Power</hi> could <hi>forgive</hi> Man the ſin he had committed, yet conſidered in the <hi>Decree</hi> he had made of puniſhing his Sin, and as a <hi>Governour</hi> bound to maintain it, ſo he was <hi>hindred</hi> from the exerciſe of that power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> No creature could poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly reverſe that <hi>Decree,</hi> nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piate the violation of this <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours Authority,</hi> for want of a Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction which He demanded. For
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:41913:80"/>where was the Creature that could give it? <hi>Angels</hi> withdraw from the <hi>brightneſs</hi> of Gods <hi>Glory,</hi> how then would they flee from the <hi>Fire</hi> of his <hi>wrath! Man</hi> cannot bear the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due to one of his <hi>own,</hi> how then would he ſuſtain the <hi>ſins</hi> of a <hi>World!</hi> Had either of them been deputed to this Task, they had ſunk under it, poor Mankind had been loſt, and God ſtill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcil'd: For to the work of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying him <hi>Srength</hi> as well as <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence</hi> is required; but the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at beſt is too <hi>weak</hi> to <hi>intercede;</hi> the <hi>price</hi> of its ſuffering too <hi>mean,</hi> the merit of which cannot extend to another; and ſo Divine Juſtice inſtead of accepting would quite <hi>devour</hi> the <hi>Sacrifice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore it was neceſſary to our recovery one ſhould undertake for us, that could anſwer the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the <hi>Decree</hi> by his <hi>Sufferings,</hi>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:41913:81"/>and ſupply the defects both of Men and Angels by the <hi>Innocence</hi> and <hi>Worth</hi> of a Sacrifice; <hi>Innocence</hi> to <hi>prepare,</hi> and <hi>Worth</hi> to <hi>crown</hi> the <hi>Oblation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that Chriſt was thus qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified to appear in our ſtead, may be eaſily evinc'd, if we will but conſider either the purity of his <hi>Humane nature,</hi> which was <hi>without ſpot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.19. Rom. 9.5.</note> or the <hi>Majeſty of his Perſon,</hi> who is <hi>God bleſſed for ever.</hi> The firſt of theſe would ſerve to make his <hi>Offering holy;</hi> the latter would give it <hi>infinite value;</hi> by both which he was fitted to pay our debt, and bear all the wrath of his Father due to our ſins.</p>
            <p>And that He actually did what He was ſo qualified to perform, we have the like evidence from Scripture. The whole Oeconomy of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the ſtrain of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> confirms it. The Sacrifices
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:41913:81"/>of the Old Law were Types and <hi>dark Images</hi> of this Great one that was <hi>once</hi> to be offered for the ſins of the people: The Goſpel-phraſe points altogether to this Truth; and therefore when it ſpeaks of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Mat. 20.28.</note> it calls him <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>price of ranſome,</hi> nay <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is a price by way of <hi>exchange,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.6.</note> in <hi>ſupplying our place:</hi> again we are ſaid to be <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by his Blood, reconciled through his Death,</hi> and to have <hi>redemption</hi> by his <hi>Sufferings:</hi> all which expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſignifie the <hi>proper effect of his Death</hi> was the <hi>remiſsion of our ſins.</hi> This He himſelf teſtifies, how that his <hi>Blood was ſhed for the remiſsion of ſins;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 26.28.</note> whence we may take comfort in his Death, and rejoyce in the vertue of his Attonement, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our <hi>pardon</hi> is obtain'd.</p>
            <p>Should we now with the <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> make plain words that expreſs all this, to be meer <hi>Metaphors</hi> and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:41913:82"/>
               <hi>Figures,</hi> we may as well joyn with the old <hi>Hereticks</hi> (the <hi>Valentinians</hi>) that made a <hi>Figure</hi> of his <hi>Living, Dying</hi> and <hi>Riſing;</hi> in that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the reality of his <hi>Fleſh:</hi> nor can their Opinion be more contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Faith than this: For as to hold. He was but the <hi>Image</hi> of a <hi>Man</hi> deſtroys a <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo to hold He was but the <hi>Image</hi> of a <hi>Prieſt</hi> deſtroys a <hi>Saviour.</hi> Thus to wreſt the Scripture is to wreſt it to our deſtruction: for what follows up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it? If he be not in a true ſenſe <hi>offer'd</hi> for us, we are ſtill in our ſins, the Curſe of the Law yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bides, and his Death becomes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unprofitable, when it brings us deliverance but in <hi>ſhadow.</hi> I might add how his ſuffering up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any other account than in our <hi>ſtead</hi> to redeem us, has nothing of juſtice in it, and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not demonſtrate the juſtice of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other;
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:41913:82"/>whereas <hi>his Blood and the declaring of Gods righteouſneſs</hi> are joyned together:
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.25.</note> but if He who was all innocence in himſelf, did not bear our guilt when He ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, the Death He underwent (being properly a puniſhment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>ſins wages</hi>) would be ſo far from declaring Gods righteouſneſs, that it could onely manifeſt the Tyranny of the Inflicter.</p>
            <p>Yet theſe kind of men are the great pretenders to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> who reject the Doctrine of <hi>Satisfaction;</hi> but cannot maintain what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver without laying their ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work in <hi>impiety;</hi> which is to aſſert He was no <hi>God</hi> that ſuffer'd; where how groſly they renounce their reaſon will appear in this, that denying him to be God, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny themſelves to be True Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, and proclaim to the world their <hi>Idolatry</hi> in <hi>adoring Man.</hi>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:41913:83"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:41913:83"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:41913:84"/>But their abſurdity farther appears, when denying the Meritoriouſneſs of his <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> they can yet make his Sufferings to be merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious of <hi>Divine Power;</hi> as if there were any proportion betwixt meer humane actions and ſo high a reward. Now what Merit is this that could raiſe him to be the <hi>Head of Angels,</hi> and Governour of all created Beings; nay to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored and worſhipped <hi>equally</hi> with the <hi>Father;</hi> which <hi>Honours</hi> the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected ſervices of the whole Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation cannot reach to? May not the Heathens ſcoff at their Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, who pretending to Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſet up a <hi>made God</hi> to pray to; and expect Salvation from One who is <hi>exalted</hi> for the vertue of his ſufferings in maintaining his <hi>Religion,</hi> as <hi>they conſecrated</hi> theirs for the Gallantry of publick acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Behold! this is onely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:41913:84"/>but not to change the nature of Gentiliſm: as likewiſe it utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly overthrows the <hi>Myſtery of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> and deſtroys the <hi>Greatneſs of Divine Love;</hi> which conſiſted chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in abaſing the <hi>Deity</hi> for Mans ſake, whereas this makes it ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous and diſhonourable in thus exalting the <hi>Humanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I leave them to their Judg above, and their Books to Judges below: I ſhall now onely briefly inquire into Two things for the better opening this Point, and ſo proceed to my Second Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How Chriſts Death is the Cauſe of the remiſſion of our ſins.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From what Time we ſhould date the Benefit of that remiſſion, as it is made ours.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>How Chriſts Death is the Cauſe,</hi> &amp;c.— I anſwer thus; God the Father was mov'd for that <hi>price</hi> his
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:41913:85"/>Son layd down (which was his precious Blood) to free us from that puniſhment we deſerved in our own perſons; and to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a New Covenant with us; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering us <hi>Pardon of ſin and Eternal Life</hi> upon new eaſie terms of <hi>faith and ſincere obedience:</hi> whereas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rigorous Juſtice bore the ſway, and ſhut us all up under a a ſentence of condemnation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope of mercy. Therefore He is called the <hi>Mediator of a better Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant;</hi> and whereas in the old League we were uſed as <hi>Gibeonites</hi> and made <hi>ſlaves,</hi> in this New one (procured by Chriſt) we are treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a <hi>free People,</hi> and made ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the Privileges of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. This He ratified in his own <hi>Blood;</hi> whence his Blood is called the <hi>Blood of the New Teſtament,</hi> wherein all his promiſes of Grace are confirm'd, and the <hi>Legal Curſe</hi> done away.</p>
            <pb n="155" facs="tcp:41913:85"/>
            <p>See here the Love of a <hi>Saviour,</hi> that would thus die to reſtore us; buy our peace at the price of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and bring us terms of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo dearly purchaſed, which before we could not hope for. This ſhows the wretchedneſs of our ſtate, and the need we ſtood in of ſuch an <hi>Expiation,</hi> when He who could <hi>create</hi> us at firſt with the <hi>eaſe</hi> of a <hi>word,</hi> is not allowed to create us anew but with the <hi>pain</hi> of <hi>ſuffering.</hi> The Croſs upon which He did this work, is a ſad ſpectacle to <hi>Senſe,</hi> but a glad ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of <hi>Faith:</hi> the one preſents him <hi>naked</hi> in our <hi>Fleſh,</hi> but the other <hi>covered</hi> with our <hi>Sins;</hi> the one ſhows him in his <hi>Blood,</hi> but the other in our <hi>Guilt,</hi> the burden of which He carried up thither, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred his Fathers wrath, and at the very point of death proclaimed his Victory, <hi>It is finiſhed;</hi> which is
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:41913:86"/>all one with this, The <hi>Attonement is wrought,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Victim</hi> is ſlain.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>From what time we ſhould date the Benefit of that Remiſsion, when it is made ours?</hi> I anſwer not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from his Satisfaction, but from the time of our <hi>rightly believing</hi> in him. <hi>We are juſtified by his Blood</hi> in one ſenſe, and <hi>we are juſtified by faith in his Blood</hi> in another: His bloody Death procur'd for us the <hi>Pardon,</hi> which is nothing elſe but putting us into <hi>capacity</hi> of being <hi>pardoned;</hi> but <hi>True Faith applies</hi> the Pardon to the Soul, whereby we <hi>actually enjoy it.</hi> How Faith here will be underſtood, may be found out by comparing two places of Scripture, namely <hi>Acts</hi> 10.43. with <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19. In the one it is ſaid, <hi>Whoſoever believeth in him ſhall receive remiſsion of ſins:</hi> in the other, <hi>Repent and be converted, that your ſins may be blotted out:</hi> ſo that True
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:41913:86"/>Faith is the Principle of a new life, the beginning of <hi>Sanctification;</hi> when the Heart is reſign'd up to God, and with ſincere reſolutions turns to him. No Faith can <hi>juſtifie</hi> us but as Faith that thus worketh: for as God will take no unſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied perſon to his Glory, ſo neither will He ſeal to him in that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>pardon of ſin</hi> here, which is the earneſt of that Glory.</p>
            <p>Truſt not then to his <hi>Wounds</hi> if thou beareſt not the <hi>marks</hi> of them in thy <hi>Soul;</hi> rely not on his Death, if ſin in thee be not crucified. They were Reprobate Jews that turn'd his Paſſion into a <hi>Sight,</hi> and came off not wounded, but true Chriſtians are <hi>pierced</hi> with <hi>beholding</hi> him, and find it operative upon their lives. Should we be <hi>juſtified</hi> without doing any thing on our part, obedience to Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands would rather be a <hi>Gift</hi> than
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:41913:87"/>a <hi>Debt;</hi> whereas the Goſpel en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns it us as <hi>neceſſary</hi> to pleaſe Him; let us then ſo come to his Grave, as not idly to <hi>bury</hi> our ſelves there; for we are but <hi>dead men</hi> in doing ſo; neither will our Maſter be found, ſince the Angel can tell us, <hi>He is not there but is riſen;</hi> whence we ought not to reſt in that place, but go forth to <hi>ſeek</hi> him. All the vertue that is in the <hi>Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> comes out to thoſe that <hi>riſe</hi> and reſemble him who is riſen, <hi>That like as he was raiſed from the dead by the glory of the Father, ſo they likewiſe might walk in newneſs of life.</hi> Thus much for the Firſt Obſervable.</p>
            <p>I proceed to handle the Second Propoſition.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>That there are proper and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Advantages in Chriſts riſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove that death— yea rather is riſen again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the time Chriſt ſlept in the
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:41913:87"/>
               <hi>Grave</hi> was a time of gloomineſs and thick darkneſs: but here God ſpeaks as he did in the old Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Let there be light:</hi> His <hi>riſing</hi> bring us <hi>day</hi> and the joyes of it; wherein <hi>Death</hi> has loſt all its <hi>ſpoyls,</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> his <hi>victory; Sin</hi> has ſpent all its <hi>force,</hi> and <hi>Mercy triumphs;</hi> the <hi>Synagogue</hi> it ſelf <hi>ends,</hi> and our <hi>Church begins.</hi> A Day very pleaſant in the ſpeculation! but may no doubt come in, that it is artificially fram'd and deviſed by Chriſtians? Truly doubts cannot be hindred, where corruption and infidelity ſo much reigns; but the reaſon of our doubting is taken away by the clear <hi>evidence</hi> that is given us of his <hi>Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you ask <hi>what that is,</hi> behold! it is grounded upon <hi>Prophets</hi> that <hi>fortell; Eye-witneſſes</hi> that <hi>confirm,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> himſelf <hi>atteſting</hi> the truth of both by the power of his <hi>Spirit</hi>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:41913:88"/>that worked in the Preachers, to make this Point undeniable. To the <hi>Prophets St.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> appeals for convincing the <hi>Jews;</hi> and <hi>St. Paul</hi> makes it a ſtanding proof, how He <hi>roſe again according to the Scriptures.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>Eye-witneſſes</hi> are produc'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> not onely a few Women and Apoſtles whom he had choſen, but <hi>Five hundred Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren at once:</hi> and thoſe He ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to were not ſo much conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable for their number as for their <hi>nicety</hi> in believing; men that had ſcruples of <hi>ſenſe</hi> which kept them from being <hi>deceived,</hi> as well as ſcruples of <hi>concience,</hi> which kept them from <hi>deceiving</hi> others. The firſt of theſe is manifeſt from hence, That they would not thoroughly believe <hi>He was riſen</hi> (though they ſaw him) till they were convinc'd by the very <hi>touch:</hi> the latter is cleer from that <hi>Doctrine</hi> they em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:41913:88"/>which forbad the <hi>leaſt ſin;</hi> and how can we imagine they durſt propagate a <hi>Cheat</hi> under all diſcouragements, when they knew they not onely ran the hazard of loſing their Lives (as they did by profeſſing him) but their Hopes too of a better life (the onely <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor</hi> of their Profeſſion) from which a <hi>Lye</hi> would certainly exclude them. Add to this the <hi>Spirit</hi> they received, the Wonders they wrought, and the <hi>Succeſs</hi> they had in their <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> when their Doctrine ſpread through the world from poor naked beginnings meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the force of this <hi>Article,</hi> it ſhows the Body of their Maſter was not ſtoln away (as the Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <hi>abſurdly</hi> reported) but that God himſelf was <hi>riſen</hi> to defend them. Theſe things well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd (if they amount not to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration</hi>)
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:41913:89"/>yet afford ſo <hi>rational a proof,</hi> as will engage our aſſent to the Truth, and convince us of folly in denying it.</p>
            <p>Now the Advantages of Chriſts <hi>Riſing</hi> above <hi>his Death</hi> have a double aſpect; for they either relate to Chriſt or to Us.</p>
            <p>Firſt to Chriſt, and ſo the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of his Reſurrection is ſeen in theſe Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It juſtified the <hi>Innocence</hi> of his <hi>Humanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When Chriſt was laid hold of, and carried away to be condemn'd by the <hi>Jews,</hi> then his very <hi>Cauſe</hi> ſeem'd to be given up: It was counted criminal with them that He would ſubmit to an <hi>Arreſt,</hi> and a ſufficient evidence to make him a Malefactor, that He did ſo tamely yield to the <hi>Trial.</hi> But when He endured the <hi>Sentence</hi> to
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:41913:89"/>be pronounced, went patiently to his <hi>Croſs,</hi> and ſuffer'd his Body to be faſtned with the <hi>nails,</hi> as if He had the <hi>guilt</hi> of a <hi>Slave</hi> with the <hi>puniſhment,</hi> here was the <hi>Hour</hi> to overcome Truth, and the <hi>Power of darkneſs</hi> to cover him, who is <hi>the light of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But his <hi>Riſing from death</hi> remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that <hi>Eclipſe,</hi> cleard that <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence,</hi> by the <hi>diſtinction</hi> it made of his <hi>Fate,</hi> when the Vileneſs of his Execution gave Authority to the Charge. This cauſed ſuch bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in <hi>Peter</hi> to plead for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and return the fault upon his Perſecutors (which He was ſo guilty of himſelf) <hi>Ye have denyed the holy one and the juſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 3.14.</note> and he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds farther to aggravate their Crime, and maintain the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of his Cauſe by that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Argument <hi>of Gods raifing</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:41913:90"/>
               <hi>him from the dead.</hi> Now it is eaſie for any one to conclude, that had our Lord been an Impoſtor, or an evil doer, he could not riſe; ſuch kind of men would ſurely rot in the Grave, and know no other Reſurrection than that of the laſt Day to a worſe Judgment; becauſe for God to <hi>puniſh</hi> them with <hi>Death here,</hi> and allow them preſently to <hi>riſe,</hi> that ſo they might confirm their own follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in thoſe Errors they taught, and thoſe Evils they practiſed; here a work of <hi>Divinity</hi> would be employed to deſtroy the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of it, which is a flat contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to his Goodneſs. Chriſt therefore by his <hi>riſing</hi> had a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony from Heaven of his upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the <hi>Evidence ſeal'd</hi> by <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipoteoce</hi> it ſelf, That He was the True Prophet which came into the world.</p>
            <pb n="165" facs="tcp:41913:90"/>
            <p n="2">2. It declared the Divinity of his Power; <hi>For He raiſed up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> Now to <hi>raiſe the Dead</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the ſtrength of a <hi>Finite Agent;</hi> and to <hi>reſtore</hi> things as well as <hi>create</hi> them does equally require an <hi>Almighty hand;</hi> both which works not being to be found in <hi>Nature,</hi> the <hi>Heatheris</hi> (thence taking their meaſures) judg'd them <hi>Impoſsible</hi> to be done: which is an <hi>unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> limiting of the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> when Men will not conſider what <hi>reſerves</hi> of <hi>Power</hi> He ought to have that is the Fountain of all the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Creatures.</p>
            <p>That Chriſt would thus raiſe up himſelf, He in his life-time foretold, and He particularly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals to the Divinity of that act (He would one day ſhow) as a ſign of his Authority to purge that <hi>Temple</hi> which they profan'd.
<note place="margin">2 Joh. 19.</note> And
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:41913:91"/>the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> expreſly tells us how <hi>by his reſurrection from the dead He was declared to be the Son of God with power;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.4.</note> that is with power He had in <hi>himſelf</hi> to <hi>give life,</hi> not with power his Father alone put forth in quickning him; for then his Riſing would be common to him with others. But did not the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles He wrought (when living) declare him likewiſe to be the <hi>Son of God?</hi> Not ſo convincingly as this: for the Wonders He then did, meer men (ſuch were the <hi>Prophets</hi>) had the Priviledg of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before him; but none except the <hi>Son of God</hi> could thus <hi>riſe;</hi> much leſs did his <hi>dying</hi> reveal him in that Majeſty, which could on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare him to be the <hi>Son of Man</hi> with <hi>weakneſs.</hi> For what more argues it then to <hi>dye?</hi> what greater ſcandal of that weakneſs
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:41913:91"/>than to die on the <hi>Croſs?</hi> wherein the <hi>Godhead</hi> ſtooped to the loweſt infirmities of Fleſh, and the worſt malice of his Perſecutors. Then his Enemies could grow bold, and ſcoffingly demand ſome proof of his Power, and the contemptible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that ſtate He was in (which hid all his Greatneſs) made them ask ſuch a ſign of it as that was of <hi>ſaving himſelf;</hi> which, if granted, had kept the world from being ſaved.</p>
            <p>But his <hi>Riſing from death</hi> had all marks of glory in it; the <hi>breaking up</hi> of the <hi>Sepulcher,</hi> the <hi>Miniſtry of Angels,</hi> the <hi>ſhaking of Earth,</hi> and <hi>the trembling of Keepers;</hi> which were but ſeveral wayes of <hi>Homage</hi> due to the <hi>Power</hi> of his <hi>Reſurrection.</hi> Here He diſcovered himſelf to be truly God, and confirm'd the Faith of his Diſciples with the Reaſon
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:41913:92"/>they had to worſhip him;</p>
            <p n="3">3. It inveſted him in his Rights, and put him into actual poſſeſſion of his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>This was the <hi>Covenant</hi> betwixt Him and his Father, that He ſhould firſt make Attonment for ſin by his Death, and receive af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the reward of that work in <hi>Dominion.</hi> Hence we read how <hi>for becoming obedient to Death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>even the Death of the Croſs, He was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore highly exalted;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 110.7.</note> 
               <hi>for drinking of the brook of the way he ſhould there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lift up his head. King</hi> He was indeed from his very birth, but He receiv'd not then <hi>the oyl of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs above his fellows:</hi> the Honour of his Anointing was as imperfect as the Form He aſſum'd, which was the Form of a Servant, where He was put under ſubjection to the Law and the Curſe, but after
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:41913:92"/>He <hi>roſe</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, He was <hi>made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> that is, <hi>actually crown'd.</hi> This is that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Matt. 19.28.</note> the <hi>Regeneration</hi> or <hi>New ſtate</hi> mention'd, namely the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the Meſſiah, which takes its date from the time of his <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> for then He ſhowed his Conqueſt of the chief Rebel <hi>Satan,</hi> by overturning the <hi>Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of his Empire, which was laid in the <hi>Grave;</hi> ſo that whereas all other Princes Glory ends in that place, this Princes <hi>Triumph</hi> there began; then He commiſſioned his Diſciples to Preach every where and Baptize, to gather him a <hi>Church</hi> made up of Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, where He would alwayes rule and preſide, when as before they continued Members of the <hi>Synagogue.</hi> And his Authority to do this He grounds upon that <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal power that was given him both</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28.</note>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:41913:93"/>
               <hi>in Heaven and in Earth,</hi> whereto He had <hi>right</hi> in his Fleſh as the <hi>Heir,</hi> but the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of it as a <hi>Poſſeſſor</hi> was ſuſpended till his riſing.</p>
            <p>Should we compare his condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under death with this his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition after it, we ſhall find a vaſt difference; for at his death He was ſo far from having the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Soveraignty, that He bore onely the looks and wore the chains of a Captive: The great mark of his Kingſhip appear'd in the <hi>Title</hi> of his <hi>Charge, King of the Jews;</hi> which being ſet over his head, and He crucified under it, it ſhowed He was the object more of mens Mockery than Fear. But when He <hi>roſe,</hi> He put on Greatneſs, took the <hi>Scepter</hi> in his <hi>hand,</hi> and made his <hi>way</hi> as a <hi>Prince</hi> by <hi>victory.</hi> Here He manifeſted the Vertue of his <hi>Kingly Office,</hi> and
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:41913:93"/>convinc'd the World of his right to command, and what obedience is due to his Laws.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I have inſiſted upon the <hi>Dignity</hi> of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> as it relates to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I ſhall next con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Advantages of it as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to us— <hi>Yea rather is riſen again.</hi> And they are theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. It manifeſted a full diſcharge of our <hi>Debt,</hi> and Gods ready ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting of that price which was paid.</p>
            <p>When a <hi>Surety</hi> that undertakes anothers Debt is caſt into <hi>priſon</hi> by the <hi>Creditor,</hi> if he comes out of it, it argues the <hi>Creditor</hi> is fully ſatisfied: ſo Chriſts coming out of the <hi>Grave</hi> (whether He was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the Judg for our offences) declares the obligation is taken off, and no more left for Him to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. To this purpoſe the Apoſtle
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:41913:94"/>ſpeaks,
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.25.</note> 
               <hi>That He roſe again for our Juſtification,</hi> or in other terms, to give us <hi>aſſurance</hi> by the <hi>Satisfaction</hi> of his <hi>Death</hi> that our <hi>Acquittance</hi> is obtain'd. The work of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was perform'd in the <hi>dark</hi> when <hi>He dyed;</hi> all the time He was held in the Grave, we could have no ſenſe of a deliverance; but when He who was <hi>ſlain</hi> for a <hi>Sin-offering,</hi> preſented himſelf af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards <hi>alive</hi> before the Lord, this brought us <hi>light</hi> to behold the <hi>Perfection</hi> of that Attonement.</p>
            <p>Look then on his <hi>Death</hi> as the cauſe of thy <hi>freedom,</hi> but on his <hi>Riſing</hi> as the ground of thy <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort:</hi> in the one He was the <hi>Prieſt</hi> to <hi>offer,</hi> in the other the <hi>Meſſenger</hi> to <hi>aſſure</hi> us; a preceding requiſite to give us the joy of a Saviour, and compleat our notion of his performance, when we ſhould ſee
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:41913:94"/>his love in the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of it, find out the <hi>Price</hi> He laid down for us by <hi>Death</hi> in the <hi>Power</hi> of that Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence He gave us by <hi>Life.</hi> The <hi>Scape-goat</hi> under the Law was but a poor <hi>uncomfortable Type,</hi> that had all the iniquities, ſins, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of Iſrael put upon his head, and was after this ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way into the Wilderneſs, whence he never return'd: but Chriſt that bore the ſins of the World, and entred the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited <hi>(the Grave)</hi> came out thence to bring us the news of his Expiation, and ſo made us certain of the beneſit. It was not enough with him to work our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, except we were further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned to know it: Thus He doubled the mercy of that act, when we whoſe ſtate He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd by dying, had our <hi>Fears</hi>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:41913:95"/>too <hi>heal'd</hi> by his <hi>Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is an efficient cauſe of our riſing with an <hi>identity</hi> of <hi>Body</hi> as He roſe; for we fall not in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of our Souls, but our Bodies; if therefore the ſame Body does not <hi>riſe,</hi> the notion of a <hi>Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> is deſtroyed. This power and right He has to raiſe us, is part of that Dominion he receiv'd when He roſe; whereby He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Lord of the Dead as well as the Living;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.9.</note> and He gave a pregnant inſtance of it at his <hi>riſing,</hi> when He cauſ'd the <hi>Stone</hi> to be remov'd not onely from his own, but from others Sepulchers; for <hi>He had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Bodies of Saints with him.</hi> They had long before ſlept in the duſt, and perhaps were ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>dry bones,</hi> that the queſtion might be put, <hi>Can this duſt live?</hi> yet were they quickly faſhioned
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:41913:95"/>in the earth, and built up by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their Maſters <hi>breath</hi> to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him in his <hi>Triumph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If our <hi>riſing</hi> be later than theirs, yet it is as ſure; for <hi>in him</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>ſhall all be made alive; He is become the Firſt-fruits of them that ſlept;</hi> Now the Firſt-fruits do not ſo go before other Fruits but that they are in <hi>being,</hi> though not brought to the ſame <hi>maturity;</hi> ſo though the <hi>Reſurrection of the Dead</hi> be not ripe, yet it really is <hi>begun,</hi> becauſe Chriſt is riſen. Whatever al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations befall us in death, they are but changes of Figure; no particle of us is loſt; the very leaſt <hi>mite</hi> of our Frame is put into the <hi>Treaſury,</hi> whence it will be one day taken out and reſtored. An excellent privilege Chriſts Members enjoy, to be thus quickned by their Head! otherwiſe the benefit of
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:41913:96"/>their reconciliation were ſmall, had he not proved their <hi>Life</hi> as well as their <hi>Sacrifice.</hi> It is a poor ſtopping of the <hi>Plague</hi> to enter the <hi>Gulfe,</hi> and not keep it by that Entrance from ſwallowing; but to open it that it ſhall yield up its <hi>dead,</hi> and no longer devour them, here is a <hi>rich Atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> All our hopes depend upon the ſucceſs of ſuch an Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; which we have confirmed to us by the <hi>riſing</hi> of our Lord, who has aboliſht Death, broken the <hi>tyranny</hi> of that Oppreſſor, and made it a <hi>Servant</hi> to <hi>convey</hi> us to Glory.</p>
            <p>But this is all upon ſuppoſition that we are qualified for his <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers;</hi> then we are raiſed by a <hi>Power inherent</hi> in <hi>us,</hi> whence we receive the influence of ſalvation; if we are no part of his <hi>Body,</hi> we ſhall
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:41913:96"/>however be raiſed, but by a power <hi>without us,</hi> the power of a Judge, that will ſit over us as Slaves, and pronounce the Sentence of Execution. Therefore the carnal liver can take no pleaſure in this word <hi>(Riſe):</hi> 'tis like a <hi>Rack</hi> to ſtretch his limbs on, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to him all his <hi>parts new ſet</hi> that they may be fitted for tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. All his joys are plac'd in a life here, which is the <hi>Senſes Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> but the life of another world cuts him in reflecting on it, as a Curſe that is attended with pain. Would we then make it our inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to riſe, let us live like <hi>Children of the Reſurrection,</hi> purge out all corrupt humours of <hi>Fleſh and Blood,</hi> mortifie our luſts, keep our Souls pure, and our Bodies clean, that when they are quickned, they may be raiſed to thoſe Heavenly Manſions, where the <hi>Honours</hi> of
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:41913:97"/>the <hi>Place,</hi> the <hi>delights</hi> of <hi>Viſion,</hi> and the <hi>cloathing</hi> of <hi>Immortality,</hi> will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy our utmoſt deſires, and ſhow us the vanity of this Worlds good that holds us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It has procur'd the Aſſiſtance of <hi>Gods Spirit</hi> whereby we are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and enabled to obtain the Promiſes of Eternal Life.</p>
            <p>Had not Chriſt <hi>roſe,</hi> the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter</hi> had not been ſent; indeed the promiſe of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> was made before, but it was ſhed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on none till after his <hi>Riſing.</hi> Then we read of his <hi>breathing upon the Apoſtles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 20.22.</note> which ſhowed the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority He had to beſtow it, and the <hi>Gifts</hi> that ſhould afterwards follow upon his Aſcenſion. How neceſſary the coming of the <hi>Spirit</hi> was, and conſequently how great the Advantage of his <hi>Riſing,</hi> will appear in this, That thereupon <hi>Miniſters</hi> were <hi>impowred, Wonders
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:41913:97"/>wrought,</hi> a <hi>Church gathered,</hi> and the <hi>Word</hi> made ſo <hi>powerfull</hi> in the hearts of the hearers, that they were not able to reſiſt the Doctrine of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> whereof the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were ordain'd to be <hi>Witneſſes.</hi> See this exemplified in <hi>St.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 1.22.</note> 
               <hi>Peters</hi> firſt Sermon on that Subject; which the <hi>Spirit</hi> accompanied with ſuch effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy, that thoſe who heard it were <hi>pricked to the heart, and the ſame day there were added to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three thouſand Souls:</hi> Where by the way the Temper of theſe <hi>new Converts</hi> is remarkable; for it is ſaid, <hi>They continued ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellowſhip, and and in breaking of Bread and in Prayers.</hi> They were no lovers of Novelty or Schiſm, but cloſe adherers to the Truth, and united together in Worſhip: A <hi>rich Draught</hi> this! which <hi>Peter</hi> had figur'd out to him in a former one, when <hi>he drew
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:41913:98"/>the Net to land full of great fiſhes; and for all there were ſo many, yet was not the Net broken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the ſame <hi>Spirit</hi> Chriſt ſtill rules in his <hi>Church</hi> in order to mens Converſion; whoſe work is to enlighten and convince us by the <hi>Word,</hi> to prevent us by his <hi>Grace</hi> in all our doings; to encline our wills and further them in good; without which aſſiſtance we could never by any natural ſtrength of our own either right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe or repent, and ſo be made capable of the Promiſes.</p>
            <p>I have here given a ſhort view of the <hi>Benefits</hi> of <hi>Chriſts riſing,</hi> which if we compare with the Vertue of his Death, we ſhall find good reaſon for that <hi>Emphaſis</hi> in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle— <hi>Yea rather is riſen again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What are the proper effects of each I have already mention'd: How <hi>his Death in particular contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:41913:98"/>but more eminently his Riſing, to the Saints freedom from Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> may be eaſily collected from what I have ſaid, ſo that I need not handle my <hi>Third Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular;</hi> therefore I ſhall now onely in a few words apply this Truth to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Gods <hi>Juſtifying Grace</hi> we read in the former verſe is reſtrained to his <hi>Elect,</hi> or which is all one, <hi>his peculiar people that are zealous of Good-works;</hi> the Benefits of <hi>Chriſts dying and riſing</hi> are reſtrained like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to the ſame perſons: <hi>For He is become the Author of Salvation to all them that obey him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 5.9.</note> Others are excluded from that Purchaſe; whence this Point obliges us to a duty of working, that as He died to <hi>Nature,</hi> and roſe again in the <hi>Body,</hi> ſo we might <hi>dye to Sin, and live unto Righteouſneſs, which is the Souls Reſurrection.</hi> The great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:41913:99"/>of his riſing was <hi>to bleſs us in turning away every one from his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 3.26.</note> which implyes the very nature of his <hi>Bleſsing</hi> conſiſts in the cleanſing of us from ſin; as our Taſte of hereafter conſiſts in being purified. No unclean liver can enter Heaven; for he <hi>wants</hi> the <hi>condition</hi> of Bliſs; no nor reliſh it (if granted him) becauſe of the <hi>unſutableneſs</hi> of that Glory: For the vaſt diſproportion which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thoſe objects that are pure and ſpiritual, and ſuch a mans de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that are filthy and carnal would turn the very Joyes of Heaven into a Puniſhment; ſo that either way he is miſerable; in the <hi>Denyal</hi> of Heaven he has <hi>no hope;</hi> in the <hi>Gift no pleaſure.</hi> We ſee a ſanctity of nature is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the fruition of Happineſs; and need we motives from ſome powerful example to encourage
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:41913:99"/>our obedience? I can produce no greater than in my Text; the manner of Chriſts love to us when He <hi>dyed,</hi> and the manner of his acting for us when He <hi>roſe,</hi> are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient arguments to quicken us.</p>
            <p>If we conſider his <hi>love</hi> to us when He dyed, it is the Picture of <hi>ſtrength</hi> in <hi>weakneſs;</hi> which could carry him chearfully to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to <hi>Gods wrath,</hi> the <hi>Jews malice,</hi> and <hi>Human frailty;</hi> and worked too his end by that ſubmiſſion; for he nail'd our ſins to the Croſs, when He was nail'd there him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and by death cancell'd our Bond. Such was the vertue of his <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> that it did not require a Second Offering; what is this elſe but a Pattern to our Mortification, that we would <hi>dye to ſin,</hi> as He did <hi>for it,</hi> that we need not kill it a Second time?</p>
            <p>If we conſider the manner of
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:41913:100"/>his <hi>Riſing,</hi> here <hi>ſtrength of love</hi> is viſible in the <hi>activity</hi> of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror.</hi> He roſe from the <hi>dead</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>day;</hi> ſo He would often riſe in his life-time; He lov'd <hi>Early Devotions,</hi> and <hi>Early Conqueſts;</hi> the one to ſhow his <hi>ſpeed</hi> in <hi>interceding</hi> for us, the other in <hi>comforting.</hi> How is this a Leſſon to us for fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his ſteps, and riſing to a <hi>life of Righteouſneſs</hi> in the very <hi>dawn</hi> of our Time, when the Morn is freſh, and our day begins; that as He made haſte to do us good, ſo we might to fit our ſelves for him. <hi>Youth</hi> is as much <hi>conſecrated</hi> to his <hi>ſervice,</hi> as the <hi>Morning</hi> was to his <hi>riſing;</hi> if we come late to him, we are unthankful Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; and beſides, the feebleneſs of ſuch a courſe takes off from the value of the performance.</p>
            <p>But his early leaving of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher (wherein the quickneſs of
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:41913:100"/>our Redeemer is manifeſted) does not ſo much inſtruct us in duty, as the <hi>perfectneſs</hi> of his <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> which diſcovers the abſoluteneſs of his Conqueſt. All others that were raiſed, dropt agen into their Graves; had not <hi>life</hi> ſo properly as <hi>death reſtored</hi> to them; but <hi>Chriſt being raiſed from the dead dyes no more; death hath no more dominion over him:</hi> That glorious Body of his has put off mortality, and all ſigns of it, except wee'l ſay the <hi>wound</hi> in his <hi>ſide,</hi> and the <hi>prints of the nails</hi> are; which yet He bears for another uſe, which is this: that whereas before they were <hi>Characters</hi> of his <hi>Weakneſs,</hi> they might now be <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies</hi> of his <hi>Strength;</hi> whereas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were <hi>marks</hi> of the <hi>Enemies Victory,</hi> they might now prove <hi>marks</hi> of his <hi>own.</hi> With the like ſtrength of Perfection ſhould we live to him; ſo quit the <hi>deadneſs</hi>
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:41913:101"/>of <hi>corrupt nature,</hi> as never to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit its return; infuſe ſuch a Soul into our Good works, that may make them vigorous and laſting. Thus we ſhall copy out his Death and Life in our ſelves, and bring that comfort home, Who is he that condemns? To think ſalvation for us is ſo wrought that we need not work it out our ſelves, is miſerably to delude our expectation, ſince all thoſe glorious effects which iſſue from his <hi>Dying and Riſing,</hi> are appointed to be <hi>Mercies</hi> to the <hi>doers,</hi> but Wonders onely to <hi>lookers on.</hi> Let us then <hi>put off the Old man</hi> with his deeds, and keep up the memory of our Maſter in the Newneſs of our lives, that <hi>when our Earthly Tabernacle is diſſolv'd, we may have a Building of God not made with hands, eternal in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:41913:101"/>
            <head>Books printed for and ſold by <hi>Richard Chiſwell.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>FOLIO.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>SPeed</hi>'s Maps and Geography of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and of Foreign Parts.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Cave</hi>'s Lives of the Primitive Fathers.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Cary</hi>'s Chronological Account of Ancient Time.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wanly</hi>'s Wonders of the Little World, or Hiſtory of Man.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Tho. Herbert</hi>'s Travels into <hi>Perſia, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Holyoak</hi>'s large Dictionary. Latin and Engliſh.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Ric. Baker</hi>'s Chronicle of <hi>England,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cauſin</hi>'s Holy Court.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wilſon</hi>'s compleat Chriſtian Dictionary.</item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Wilkin</hi>'s Real Character, or Philoſophical Language.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pharmacopaeia Regalis Collegii Medicorum. Londinenſis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Judge <hi>Jone</hi>'s Reports of Caſes in Common-Law.</item>
               <item>Judge <hi>Vaughan</hi>'s Reports of Caſes in Common-Law.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cave Tabulae Eccleſiaſticorum Scriptorum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hobb</hi>'s Leviathan.</item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Bacon</hi>'s Advancement of Learning,</item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Sermons.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Will. Dugdale</hi>'s Baronage of <hi>England</hi> in 2 Vol.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Raranelli Bibliotheca Theologica</hi> 3 Vol.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>QUARTO.</head>
               <item>THe ſeveral Informations exhibited to the Committee appointed by Parliament to inquire into the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>London,</hi> 1667.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Godwin</hi>'s Roman Antiquities.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Littleton</hi>'s Dictionary.</item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Nicholſon</hi> on the Church Catechiſm.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:41913:102"/>
               <item>The Compleat Clark.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Pierce</hi> on Gods Decrees.</item>
               <item>Hiſtory of the late Wars of <hi>New-England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Outram de Sacrificiis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Diſwaſive from Popery.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gariſſolius de Chriſto Mediatori,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Corpus Confeſſionum Fidei.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spauhemii Dubia Evangelica</hi> 2 Vol.</item>
               <item>Dr <hi>Gibb</hi>'s Sermons.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Parkeri Diſputationes de Deo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Caryl</hi> on <hi>Job</hi> compleat, 12 parts.</item>
               <item>Deſcription and Hiſtory of the Future State of <hi>Europe,</hi> 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fowler</hi>'s Defence of the Deſign of Chriſtianity againſt <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lyford</hi>'s Diſcovery of Errors and Hereſies of the Times, 4 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Viſitation Sermon at <hi>Warrington,</hi> 1659. 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Weſt</hi>'s Aſſize-Sermon at <hi>Dorcheſter,</hi> 1671. 6 <hi>d,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Dobſon</hi>'s Sermon at Lady <hi>Farmers</hi> Funeral, 1670. 8 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Directions for Improvement of Barren Land, 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Culverwel</hi>'s Diſcourſe of the Light of Nature, 3 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Meric Caſaubon</hi>'s Letter to Dr. <hi>Du Moulin,</hi> about Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimental Philoſophy, 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Hollis</hi>'s Relation of the Unjuſt Accuſation of certain French Gentlemen charged with a Robery, 1671. 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Magiſtrates Authority aſſerted, in a Sermon by <hi>James Paſton.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>OCTAVO.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conold</hi>'s Notion of Schiſm according to the Antients with Reflections on Mr. <hi>Hales.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Poſing of the Parts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Elborow</hi>'s Rationale upon the Engliſh Service.</item>
               <item>Burnets Vindication of the Ordination of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wincheſter</hi> Phraſes.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:41913:102"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wilkin</hi>'s Natural Religion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hardcaſtle</hi>'s Chriſtian Geography and Arithmetick.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aſhton</hi>'s Apology for the Honours and Revenues of the Clergy.</item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Hollis</hi>'s Vindication of the Judicature of the Houſe of Peers in the caſe of <hi>Skinner.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— Juriſdiction of the Houſe of Peers in caſe of Appeals.</item>
               <item>— Juriſdiction of the Houſe of Peers in caſe of Impoſitions.</item>
               <item>— Letter about the Biſhops Vote in Capital Caſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Xenophontis Cyropoedia.</hi> Gr. Lat.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duporti Verſio Pſalmorum Graeca.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Grews</hi> Idea of Philological Hiſtory continued on Roots.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spaniards</hi> Conſpiracy againſt the State of <hi>Venice.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Batei Elenchus motuum nuperorum in Anglia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Erown</hi>'s <hi>Religio Medici.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Several Tracts of Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> of <hi>Eton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi>'s Life.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Tillotſons</hi> Rule of Faith.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gregorii Etymologicon Parvum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paſſoris Grammatica Grae. Novi Teſtimenti,</hi> 4 s.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Roſſei Gnomologicon Poeticum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gouge</hi>'s word to Saints and Sinners.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Simpſon</hi>'s Chymical Anatomy of the <hi>Yorkshire</hi> Spaws; with a Diſcourſe of the Original of Hot-Springs and other Fountains; and a Vindication of Chymical Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, 3 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—His Hyrological Eſſays; with an Account of the Allom-works at <hi>Whitby,</hi> and ſome Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations about the Jaundice. 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Cox</hi>'s Diſcourſe of the Intereſt of the Patient, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to Phyſick and Phyſicians, and Detection of the Abuſes practiſed by the Apothecaries. 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:41913:103"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Organon Salutis:</hi> Or an Inſtrument to cleanſe the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach: with divers New Experiments of the Vertue of Tobacco and Coffee: To which is prefixed a Preface of Sir <hi>Henry Blunt.</hi> 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Problems.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Cave</hi>'s Primitive Chriſtianity, in three parts.</item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe of the Nature, Ends, and Difference of the two Covenants, 1672. 2 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ignatius Fuller</hi>'s Sermons of Peace and Holineſs, 1672. 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lipſius</hi>'s Diſcourſe of Conſtancy. 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Willis Angliciſms</hi> Latiniz'd. 3 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Buckler of State and Juſtice againſt <hi>France</hi>'s Deſign of Univerſal Monarchy, 1673.</item>
               <item>A Free Conference touching the Preſent State of <hi>England</hi> at home and abroad, in order to the deſigns of <hi>France,</hi> 1673. 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi> of Confirmation. 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Myſtery of Jeſuitiſm, third and fourth part. 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sanderſon Judicium Academ. Oxonienſ. de Solenni Liga.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Samways</hi> Unreaſonableneſs of the Romaniſts. 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Record</hi> of Urins. 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Aſhton</hi>'s Caſes of Scandal and Perſecution. 1674. 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>DUODECIMO.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>FArnabii Index Rhetoricus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ciceronis Orationes ſelectae.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hodders Arithmetick.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Horatius Minellii.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sands</hi> Ovids Metamorphoſis.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Grotius de Veritate Religionis Chriſtianae.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Hacket</hi>'s Chriſtian Conſolations.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:41913:103"/>
            <list>
               <head>VICESIMO QUARTO.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>cius Florus.</hi> Lat.—</item>
               <item>—Id. Truth. 19<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Crums of Comfort.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Valentine</hi>'s Devotions.</item>
               <item>Guide to Heaven.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Books lately printed.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>illim</hi>'s Diſplay of Herauldry with large Additions.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Hiſtory of the Reformation of the Church of <hi>England. folio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Burlace</hi>'s Hiſtory of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Herodoti Hiſtoria. Grae. Lat. fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>John Jeniſon</hi>'s Additional Narrative about the Plot.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cole</hi>'s Latin and Engliſh Dictionary with large Additions, 1679.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William</hi>'s Sermon before the Lord Mayor, <hi>Octob.</hi> 12.79.</item>
               <item>— Hiſtory of the Gunpowder Treaſon.</item>
               <item>— Impartial Conſideration of the Speeches of the Five Jeſuits executed for Treaſon. <hi>fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Relation of the Maſſacre of the Proteſtants in <hi>France.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tryals of the Regicides. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dangerfield</hi>'s Narrative of the Pretended Presbyterian Plot.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>James Brome</hi>'s Two Faſt Sermons. The Famine of the Word threatned to Iſrael, and Gods call to weeping and mourning.</item>
               <item>Account of the Publick Aſſairs in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſince the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the late Plot.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Jane</hi>'s Faſt Sermon before the Houſe of Commons, <hi>April</hi> 11. 1679.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:41913:104"/>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Two Letters written upon the Diſcovery of the late Plot. 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Decree made at <hi>Rome</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                  <hi>March,</hi> 1679. condemning ſome Opinions of the Jeſuits and other Caſuiſts. 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>John James</hi> Viſitation Sermon, <hi>April</hi> 9. 1671. 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>John Cave</hi>'s Faſt Sermon on 30 <hi>Jan.</hi> 1679. 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— His Aſſize Sermon at <hi>Leiceſter, July</hi> 31. 1679. 4<hi rend="sup">to</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Certain Genuine Remains of the Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> in Arguments Civil, Moral, Natural, Medical, Theological and Biblio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphical; with a large Account of all his Works, by Mr. <hi>Thomas Teniſon.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Puller</hi>'s Diſcourſe of the Moderation of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Original of all the Plots in Chriſtendome; with the Danger and Remedy of Schiſm: by Dr. <hi>William Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> Maſter of Jeſus Colledge <hi>Cambridge.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe of Supreme Power and Common Right, by a Perſon of Quality. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Edw. Bagſhaw</hi>'s Diſcourſe upon Select Texts againſt the Papiſt and Socinian. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Books now in the Preſs.</head>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Ruſhworth</hi>'s Hiſtorical Collections: The ſecond Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume. <hi>fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—His large and exact Account of the Tryal of the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> with all the Circumſtarices prelimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary to concomitant with, and ſubſequent upon the ſame to his death. <hi>fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Remarques relating to the ſtate of the Church of the three firſt Centuries, wherein are interſperſ'd Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions on a Book, called A View of Antiquity: By <hi>J. H.</hi> Written by <hi>A. S.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:41913:104"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
